<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Qoherences</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/</link><description>News for quantum people</description><atom:link href="https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:harold.ollivier@linksights.io"&gt;Harold Ollivier&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 05:29:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Perspectives on Quantum Computing: NISQ and beyond</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/perspectives_on_quantum_computing/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgcc2fb75" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgcc2fb75"&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgcc2fb75"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM-Q classification algorithm developed for high energy physics at CERN is apparently on par with its classical counterpart (classification performance and running time).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a global shortage of talents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the proponents of superconducting qubits are happy with their solution as they think it's what's the easiest so you can focus on what goes wrong. Additionally, Google's tunable couplers really seem to help a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More and more discussions with industrial use-cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having one fault-tolerant logical qubit within 5 years seems a reasonable goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QC need to integrate itself into the HPC value chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6a51b55" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6a51b55"&gt;Program of the conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6a51b55"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum algorithms for the NISQ area and beyond: Iordanis Kerenidis (CNRS / QCWare)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum supremacy using a programmable superconducting processor: Charles Neill (Google Quantum AI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum computing and its applications in chemistry and physics: Ivano Tavernelli (IBM Zürich)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-stack quantum computing with superconducting qubits: Nicolas Didier (Rigetti)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realizing fault-tolerant superconducting quantum processors: Andreas Wallraff (ETH Zürich)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programmable quantum simulators and sensors on atomic platforms: Rick van Bijnen (U. Innsbruck)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Round tables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0ab426d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0ab426d"&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0ab426d"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6acc30c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6acc30c"&gt;Iordanis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6acc30c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We currently have two kind of tools for NISQ: Euristics (QAOA and VQE) and algorithms (HHL, QML, Neural nets, …). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong with euristics, it's just that we don't quite know how to prove the speedup. But hey, if it works in practice, it should be made available to users because they are accustomed to deal with euristics! These euristics help solving problems of optimisation under constraints (pretty much any field, from finance to transportation) for QAOA and energy minimisation problems (found in chemistry and pharma) for VQE. Both work by using a quantum machine to speedup a hybrid quantum + classical optimisation loop. Of course, for any euristics, you know it's not going to work for all problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That will imply a lot of trial and error, hence more quantum datascience in the future to bring solutions to customers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As for the algorithms based on HHL (a lot of QML), the crux is fast dataloading. In fact, these algorithms were introduced using an assumption that fast data loading was possible (ie transform classical data describing the problem to solve, to quantum usable data for the algorithm). This "fine-print" assumption came to light since Ewin Tang's dequantization paper from july 2018. It showed that the argument "Quantum computers access an exponentially large computational space hence are more powerful than their classical counterpart" fell apart: under similar "fast dataloading" assumption (in fact efficient sampling) you can find efficient classical algorithms to do the same task. But this is not the end of the story. As for euristics, if it works in practice, you should use it. And apparently, it works in practice. Iordanis reported the following figures for recommendation systems (using typical instance size): 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum: 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical: 10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum inspired (dequantized version): 10&lt;sup&gt;33&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Main messages from Iordanis:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The key for the field now is to find something that we can run and that is impactful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications should drive the development of NISQ machines now. We cannot wait to build the machine and then start looking for use-cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org567e0fa" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org567e0fa"&gt;Charles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org567e0fa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We got a lot of pictures and explanations around the peculiarity of Google's design (superconducting). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The most interesting one (which they seem to be the only ones to have) is the presence of tunable couplers between their neighbouring qubits. This allows a "hardware" decoupling and in turn releases spots on your qubit pulse timeline to perform useful quantum operations (instead of pulsing the qubits in the background to decouple them via software). This allows for more aggressive / faster gates without decreasing the quality of them. The result is more gates per qubit. For instance: 2 qubit gates are reported at 12ns, with a 0.5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; fidelity. You can also go for more parallelism (many gates on different qubits at the same time). It also reduces the flux for applying gates and thus the cross-talk errors between qubits.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charles then talked about how Google results can be verified (since we can't use a classical computer to check the computation, and Google is the only company able to run the experiment). The approach is a physics one: Show that your error model  seems to work well up to the largest instances they can simulate classically, and that the data you get from larger instances seems to be inline. That's a good approach from a physics perspective. Not a very convincing one from the cryptographic point of view. There exists solutions for this last part though, but they are not quite focused on that yet (but they probably should).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charles went on showing chemistry applications, basically stating they are starting working on real life problems with industries. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last mentioned: their work on using a fixed always-on Hamiltonian for 22 qubits and performing analog control. Didn't quite say what the idea behind this was, but I suspect building simulators of quantum physical systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgea01388" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgea01388"&gt;Ivano&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgea01388"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part of the talk was devoted to introducing IBM's hardware and software (QisKit). One notable mention: IBM is using a superconducting architecture, but without tunable couplers. But that didn't prevent them on making progress. Their measure of performance (the quantum volume = # qubits x # gates you can apply to them) has been greatly enhanced and is on a trend of doubling every year (at least that's what the first 3 points show).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ivano's talk was impressive as they really dug into chemistry problems and trying to understand how better the quantum algorithms were. Alas, it's only for small instances as NISQ devices don't have enough computing power yet to start competing with classical software on larger molecules. But, if you take their work as a calibration phase, it is promising: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you get answers that more closely match analytical solutions (when you have them) than what the classical algorithms are able to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM seems to have a technique to extrapolate results from noisy computations via classical post-processing that looks interesting… or I might have misunderstood and they in fact didn't need to extrapolate and were able to get the result directly from their quantum algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again we have a lot of ad-hoc work for solving problems and see how to mitigate errors on real computations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most impressive part of the day: IBM has been partnering with CERN for classification of high energy physics events collected at ATLAS. The quantum algorithm (QSVM) is on par with the classical one in terms of quality (small advantage for the quantum one – 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt; improvement, not quite significant). According to Ivano, there has not been much tuning done yet. On top of that it is fast (running at the micro second level). That's impressive. Looking for the details of a forthcoming paper.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6f05ddf" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6f05ddf"&gt;Nicolas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6f05ddf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Interesting presentation of their full-stack approach. It's really full-stack: designing the chip, the controllers, the PCB boards, the cryostats, … and software as well. Very similar settings and techniques to IBM and Google. They invested a lot (like the others) on error mitigation, reducing cross-talk and latency. Interestingly, they developed a parametric compiler that would compile once and reuse the result of the compiled sequence with different parameters. That would reduce greatly the latency as compiling would otherwise be needed each time you change a parameter in your gates (even though it is only a small change). They also use active reset (instead of letting their qubits decohere).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We went at length into some of their work for reducing flux noise. Long story short: they achieve a fidelity &amp;gt; .99 on their C-Z gates
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfe96fc8" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfe96fc8"&gt;Andreas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfe96fc8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One key point from Andreas is that excellent academic labs are having trouble keeping the people in academia. Part of the group was bought at once by microsoft. That's a long term problem for innovation as all the settings of Google, IBM, Rigetti are based on academic research. So there needs to be someone thinking ahead in these companies as to not deplete academia too much. On top of that, private companies have been investing way more money than academia into building devices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
About his talk: I loved it! someone interested in quantum error correction and showing how to do it. They achieved an error detection code with 7 qubits (3 ancillas, 4 logical qubits). The plan is to do error correction with 17 and 49 qubits using surface codes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The reported errors are a few percents on 2 qubit gates. For stabilizer measurements, with 2 non trivial Pauli's it's about 95%, and 81% for 4 Pauli's. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org38a4a4f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org38a4a4f"&gt;Rick&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org38a4a4f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very different approach here, but very NISQ-y. They use ion traps to simulate natural quantum processes. That means you engineer a system with some degree of control. You tune the parameters so that the effective Hamiltonian that your ions feel is related to the Hamiltonian you are interested in (if you find the solution for one, you get the solution for the second). The nice point, is that most of the problems you solve are eigenvalue / eigenvectors, hence you are in principle able to check if the solution is correct (or to which degree it is correct). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org9f5898e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9f5898e"&gt;Round tables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9f5898e"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One key point: users are not intending to buy quantum computers, but rather rent it. However, they don't want to rent it over the cloud. They want to finely understand their architecture, and limitations, as they already do for their HPC capabilities. QC makers and software companies should integrate into the HPC value chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why superconducting: it's so simple, that you can focus on all the other things that go wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The materials bill for QC is low (a few $m). What is expensive is the knowledge you have to build to make it work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google gate performance should allow fault tolerant QC with a 1:1000 ratio. Having 1 logical qubits seems to be a reasonable goal for the next 5 yrs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to talents is hard, but education programs at ETH have proved successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/perspectives_on_quantum_computing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 03:42:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #7</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-29/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org95dc4b2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org95dc4b2"&gt;General Public Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org95dc4b2"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org73f9f5b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org73f9f5b"&gt;A new quantum data classification protocol brings us nearer to a future 'quantum internet' – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-classification-protocol-nearer-future.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org73f9f5b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org – Autonomous University of Barcelona&lt;/i&gt; – UAB researchers have been looking at an algorithm for data clustering for quantum states.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb8fc3bc" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb8fc3bc"&gt;Tom O'Brien explains why we need a quantum computer – &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qHJzyOU2Pls&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb8fc3bc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Youtube – University of Leiden, Tim O'Brien&lt;/i&gt; – Good video showing why quantum computers might be efficient for quantum chemistry.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9a00167" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9a00167"&gt;Quantum physics: Our study suggests objective reality doesn't exist – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-physics-reality-doesnt.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9a00167"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Experimental evidence that quantum reality is not a very well defined thing. In fact  the ability to reconcile two observers interpretation of their experimental results is not  granted by quantum mechanics. But it can be used as a way to detect when quantum mechanics actually become classical.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0329320" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0329320"&gt;Nanooptical traps: A promising building block for quantum technologies – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-nanooptical-block-quantum-technologies.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0329320"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Researchers are reporting better nanooptical traps that hold atoms much longer than before. That's interesting as a way to design and control  light and matter interactions which would be used in quantum computing and quantum internet applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org749b010" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org749b010"&gt;Quantum Volume: A Yardstick To Measure The Performance Of Quantum Computers – &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/moorinsights/2019/11/23/quantum-volume-a-yardstick-to-measure-the-power-of-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org749b010"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Forbes – Paul Smith-Goodson&lt;/i&gt; – The case for quantum volume as a measure of performance for quantum hardware. That's a sensible metric pushed forward by IBMQ and Quantum Benchmark. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc19efd0" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc19efd0"&gt;Researchers reach milestone in quantum standardisation – &lt;a href="https://eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2019-11/uow-rr112519.php"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc19efd0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U Waterloo&lt;/i&gt; – Well now, how do you compute the performance of quantum computers in practice (now that you know you should report quantum volume as explained in the previous entry). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org00064b2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org00064b2"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org00064b2"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga9b32b2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga9b32b2"&gt;IQM Finland raises €11.6 million to speed up advancements in quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://www.eu-startups.com/2019/07/iqm-finland-raises-e11-6-million-to-speed-up-advancements-in-quantum-computing/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga9b32b2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;EU Startups – IQM Finland, Matadero QED, Maki.vc, MIG Fonds, OpenOcean, Tesi (Finnish Industry Investment), and Vito Ventures Fund&lt;/i&gt; – The startup raised money in July to build scalable cryogenic hardware for quantum computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6febf24" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6febf24"&gt;For faster quantum computing, Microsoft builds a better qubit – &lt;a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/for-faster-quantum-computing-microsoft-builds-a-better-qubit/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6febf24"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;CNet – Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announced to be very close to having topological qubits working. Apparently thanks to improvements in the way qubits controllers are wired.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org38c4a41" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org38c4a41"&gt;HYRAX: The quantum discovery framework – &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/rahko_quantumtech-quantumsoftware-quantumcomputing-activity-6600317570186866688-NSdX/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org38c4a41"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rahko&lt;/i&gt; – The recently funded company did release a framework for machine learning with backends for some of the leading quantum computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga779dae" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga779dae"&gt;D'Arpanet à Internet : une histoire des réseaux – &lt;a href="https://interstices.info/dossier/darpanet-a-internet-une-histoire-des-reseaux/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga779dae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Interstices&lt;/i&gt; – In french: very interesting series of articles about ARPANET enlightning to read now that we are building a quantum internet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3ff0c70" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3ff0c70"&gt;France's GDR Quantum Information from Fundamental Aspects to Experiments organised its 10th annual colloqium early november – &lt;a href="https://iqfacolloq2019.sciencesconf.org/data/pages/BoA_iqfacolloq2019_CNRS_4.pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3ff0c70"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;GDR IFQA&lt;/i&gt; – Read the abstracts to have a glimpse of France's research on quantum information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org8499a55" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8499a55"&gt;NTT taps NASA to take on Google and IBM in quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://asia.nikkei.com/Business/Technology/NTT-taps-NASA-to-take-on-Google-and-IBM-in-quantum-computing"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8499a55"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nikkei Asian Review – NTT, NASA&lt;/i&gt; – NTT is partnering with NASA to develop quantum computing and go for a race with Google and IBM already quite far ahead. Interesting to see o non US based company stepping in to build a quantum computer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org01d2b4d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org01d2b4d"&gt;PsiQuantum raises big money ($230m) – &lt;a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/2019/11/16/bristol-professors-secretive-quantum-computing-start-up-raises/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org01d2b4d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;PsiQuantum&lt;/i&gt; – PsiQuantum, founded by Jeremy O’Brien, has secured the funds from investors including a venture capital fund started by former Google executive Andy Rubin. The photonics quantum computing is increasingly looking like a feasible alternative to other technologies to built fault tolerant quantum computers. They are going to work on skipping the NISQ phase altogether.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbf0c300" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbf0c300"&gt;D-Wave sticks with its approach to quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/11/15/d-wave-sticks-with-its-approach-to-quantum-computing/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbf0c300"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;D-Wave&lt;/i&gt; – D-Wave partnered with VW to optimise traffic at the Lisbon Websummit. Although one might discuss whether D-Wave is doing quantum computation, I think we should see the positive side of having proof of concepts that go outside labs and go to real environments. Congrats for showing the way towards computing applications for quantum devices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgcc1ad34" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgcc1ad34"&gt;Cambridge Quantum Computing announces new release of updated software stack – &lt;a href="https://cambridgequantum.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/CQC-181119.pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgcc1ad34"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Cambridge Quantum Computing&lt;/i&gt; – That's a new software for designing / compiling circuits into an efficient representation suitable for being run on the major backends. This is important as these backends have topologies that make various optimisations required to get something useful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgefd3d0a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgefd3d0a"&gt;h-bar consultants published an overview of hardware QC companies funding rounds – &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hbar_consultant/status/1195889753423433728?s=09"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgefd3d0a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;h-bar&lt;/i&gt; – Good to see some of them generating revenue. Doesn't mean they show a positive bottom line, just that topline is greater than 0!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org80b7e65" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org80b7e65"&gt;Zeiss announces a quantum challenge – &lt;a href="https://www.zeiss.com/corporate/int/careers/events/zeiss-quantum-challenge.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org80b7e65"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Zeiss&lt;/i&gt; – The company is joining the quantum fun with a challenge centered on sensing and imaging. Deadline is march 31st 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfd446ec" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfd446ec"&gt;Xanadu receives grant from DARPA to test QML on quantum hardware – &lt;a href="https://betakit.com/xanadu-receives-grant-from-darpa-to-test-qml-performance-on-quantum-hardware/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfd446ec"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu, DARPA&lt;/i&gt; – The research project is expected to last 12 months.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org954568b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org954568b"&gt;Research Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org954568b"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc9c0529" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc9c0529"&gt;Characterizing large-scale quantum computers via cycle benchmarking – &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-13068-7"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc9c0529"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Alexander Erhard, Joel J. Wallman, Lukas Postler, Michael Meth, Roman Stricker, Esteban A. Martinez, Philipp Schindler, Thomas Monz, Joseph Emerson &amp;amp; Rainer Blatt&lt;/i&gt; – How do you benchmark the quality of quantum gates involving more that 3 - 4 qubits ? If you do tomography with imperfect state preparation and measurements, it will take for ever. Cycle benchmarking is an interesting option and has been demonstrated experimentally on ion trap QC. Related to the last entry of the General Public Articles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef1880a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgef1880a"&gt;Positions - Conferences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgef1880a"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0f55fd1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0f55fd1"&gt;Quantum Computing Theory in Practice Conference – &lt;a href="https://riverlane.io/qctip-conference/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0f55fd1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Centre for Mathematical Sciences, Cambridge | 6-8 April 2020
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org730d103" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org730d103"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org730d103"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbeeb735" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbeeb735"&gt;Neutrinos Lead to Unexpected Discovery in Basic Math – &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/neutrinos-lead-to-unexpected-discovery-in-basic-math-20191113/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbeeb735"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quanta Magazine – Stephen Parke (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), Xining Zhang (University of Chicago), Peter Denton (Brookhaven National Laboratory)&lt;/i&gt; – A beautiful fundamental result in linear algebra, giving a simple way of expressing the eigenvectors of a matrix in terms of the eigenvalues of that matrix and some submatrices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga0d6215" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga0d6215"&gt;Quantum light improves sensitivity of biological measurements – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-sensitivity-biological.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga0d6215"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Research on single photon source finds use in biology to track enzymatic reaction in real-tine. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-29/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #6</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-19/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgedd1ba8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgedd1ba8"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgedd1ba8"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfcf2e0b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfcf2e0b"&gt;The hard sell of quantum software – &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/the-hard-sell-of-quantum-software/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfcf2e0b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Why are people founding so many start-ups to build quantum software ? What are the potential use cases and what are the short term focus for these companies ?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd950afa" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd950afa"&gt;Here’s what the people who claimed Google’s quantum supremacy have to say about it – &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2019/10/inside-googles-quantum-computing-efforts/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd950afa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Google Quantum AI Lab - Ars Technica&lt;/i&gt; – Nice article with lots of pictures from inside Google's lab. Fair account on the challenges faced for hardware and software componenets, and surprisingly (or not), wiring comes out as one of the most challenging ones. But that doesn't look like it's unsolvable though when you add industrial engineering and processing. You can also read Google's blog post about their experieent and settings &lt;a href="https://ai.googleblog.com/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-using-programmable.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org06b8a2f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org06b8a2f"&gt;Quantum internet: at the verge of an emerging technology – &lt;a href="https://blog.qutech.nl/index.php/2019/10/22/quantum-internet-at-the-verge-of-an-emerging-technology/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org06b8a2f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;QuTech, TU Delft&lt;/i&gt; – Nice article showing what use cases of a quantum internet will be: QKD and all sorts of cryptographic protocols, but most importantly Delegated Quantum Computation. Sensing and metrology are also on the list. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9b1ec47" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9b1ec47"&gt;Google and IBM are at odds over ‘quantum supremacy’ – an expert explains what it really means – &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/google-and-ibm-are-at-odds-over-quantum-supremacy-an-expert-explains-what-it-really-means-125827"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9b1ec47"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;T. Cubitt - The Conversation&lt;/i&gt; – JUst a quote from the short article: "This is how science and technology progresses. Not in one dramatic and revolutionary breakthrough, but in a whole series of small breakthroughs, with the academic community carefully scrutinising, criticising and refining each step along the way. Only a few of these advances and debates hit the headlines. The reality is both less dramatic and more interesting."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4b42c76" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4b42c76"&gt;Quantum Computer Made from Photons Achieves a New Record – &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/quantum-computer-made-from-photons-achieves-a-new-record/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4b42c76"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Science and Technology, China – Scientific American&lt;/i&gt; – The development of photonic quantum computing is impressive. There you trade low temperatures for extreme timing accuracy. The pro is that photons in the vaccuum are essentially decoherence free. The con is that you need to find a clever way to have photon-photon gates… 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc67afc0" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc67afc0"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc67afc0"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga8e949b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga8e949b"&gt;Alphabet's X is contributing to port some quantum tools to tensorflow – &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/TensorNetwork"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga8e949b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;X&lt;/i&gt; – Jack Hidary mentionned that the work of G. Vidal on tensor networks is being turned into a module accessible through tensor flow to help making large simulations of quantum systems easier to perform on classical computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6ccdbc5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6ccdbc5"&gt;Quantum Benchmark supports development of Google’s world-leading quantum computers – &lt;a href="https://quantumbenchmark.com/quantum-benchmark-supports-development-of-googles-world-leading-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6ccdbc5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quantum Benchmark, Google Quantum AI Lab&lt;/i&gt; – QUantum Benchmark is working with Google to improve gate efficiency and compiling. Great partnership.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0703d3a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0703d3a"&gt;HPE announces investment into IonQ – &lt;a href="https://www.hpe.com/us/en/newsroom/blog-post/2019/10/shaping-the-quantum-future.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0703d3a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ &amp;amp; HPE&lt;/i&gt; – HPE is making the choice of Trapped Ion technology as a better way to scale quantum computing experiements to commercially useful machines. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc5353d6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc5353d6"&gt;Volkswagen optimizes traffic flow with quantum computers – &lt;a href="https://www.volkswagen-newsroom.com/en/press-releases/volkswagen-optimizes-traffic-flow-with-quantum-computers-5507"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc5353d6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;VW &amp;amp; D-Wave&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum computing in practice wit VW optimizing traffic in Lisbon during the WebSummit conference. It still remains to be seen how better it solves the problem compared to classical optimization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org037ba91" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org037ba91"&gt;Xanadu is expanding it's pennylane software to include Cirq support – &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/xanaduai_xanaduaipennylane-cirq-activity-6595352592212127744-ejwx/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org037ba91"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu&lt;/i&gt; – Pennylane is now able to interact with Cirq (google's framework) so you can actually optimize a full quantum-classical hybrid algo using Cirq / Forest / Qiskit and the usual Tensorflow and Pytorch tools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7314686" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7314686"&gt;Experience quantum impact with Azure Quantum – &lt;a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/quantum/2019/11/04/announcing-microsoft-azure-quantum/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7314686"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announces the launch of Azure Quantum. Yet another player going for a cloud offering for quantum computing. This is a major change compared to when classical computing started. Quantum computing is being built on top of a very rich stack of computing and communication experience. In my opinion, this makes quantum communication and quantum computation inseparable topics, both requiring attention and investments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge616f8b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge616f8b"&gt;IonQ Partners with Microsoft to Power Azure Quantum – &lt;a href="https://ionq.com/news/november-4-2019-microsoft-partnership"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge616f8b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ &amp;amp; Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – A partnership to make Azure Quantum, well… quantum ! Two big hits for IonQ (HPE and Microsoft). Is that the revenge of the trapped Ions ? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org60ba309" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org60ba309"&gt;Micorsoft partners with Honeywell – &lt;a href="https://www.honeywell.com/en-us/newsroom/news/2019/11/the-future-of-quantum-computing?utm_source=TW&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=newsroom&amp;amp;utm_term=msquantum&amp;amp;sf111836522=1"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org60ba309"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Microsoft &amp;amp; Honeywell&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announces its partnership with Honeywell "to bring about quantum impact through Azure Quantum" (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/krystasvore/status/1191425045970612224?s=09"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbee34f5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbee34f5"&gt;AQT now supports Qiskit – &lt;a href="https://www.aqt.eu/aqt-now-supports-qiskit/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbee34f5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;AQT&lt;/i&gt; – Alpine Quantum Computing develops an Ion trap quantum computer. It reports of its compatibility with IBM qiskit devevelopment tools suite.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc0183d1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc0183d1"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc0183d1"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2ea112b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2ea112b"&gt;List of accepted papers at QIP2020 – &lt;a href="http://www.szpclab.com/qip2020#/programDetails"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2ea112b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Impressive and exciting list. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org8f56bd4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8f56bd4"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8f56bd4"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga1c2d17" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga1c2d17"&gt;PostDoc position at the Center for Theoretical Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences – &lt;a href="http://www.cft.edu.pl/new/public/links/aHR0cHMlM0ElMkYlMkZjZnRwYW4uYmlwLmdvdi5wbCUyRmZvYmplY3RzJTJGZG93bmxvYWQlMkY2NTk0NjElMkZhbm5vdW5jZW1lbnQtYWJvdXQtdGhlLWNvbXBldGl0aW9uLmh0bWw=/display"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga1c2d17"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;CTP, Polish Academy of Sciences&lt;/i&gt; – 
Announcement from Remigiusz Augusiak, to work on quantum information theory, quantum entanglement, Bell nonlocality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-19/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 05:29:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #5</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-24/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org0b646a6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0b646a6"&gt;Hot / Not Hot / Hot Again News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0b646a6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
IBM claims in &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.09534"&gt;arXiv/1910/09534&lt;/a&gt; that Google's quantum supremacy computation is not so supreme. They optimized the classical simulation and went down to 2.5 days instead of 10000+ years. So: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are much better at optmizing classical simulations of quantum algorithms than google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They did not make remarks on the quantum part, nor did they decrease the amount of elementary operations necessary to simulate the quantum computation (complexity is unchanged)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.5 minutes is 1000 times less than 2.5 days (Google's computation is performed 1000 times faster than what the supercomputer SUMMIT is able to achieve).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you conclude whether the quantum supremacy claim from Google still holds. &lt;a href="https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/breaking-the-breaking-news-or-not/"&gt;More details&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, Google has published its supremacy result – &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1666-5?fbclid=IwAR30gYaaQUI-uIAnd7e9UajLkGPXKnTKF3bqVKjajTOA1YcJK17UUYIUHxs"&gt;Nature 574, pages 505–510 (2019)&lt;/a&gt; –, and politely answered to IBM's paper saying they welcome comments on how to optimize classical algorithms, but it's better to actually test them to be sure of what you are gaining. Apparently Google's estimate was done using real sample data from supercomputers which IBM didn't do in their paper. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org5c4472f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5c4472f"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5c4472f"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6487ea0" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6487ea0"&gt;Beyond quantum supremacy: the hunt for useful quantum computers - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02936-3"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6487ea0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature - Michael Brooks&lt;/i&gt; – While some are debating about quantum supremacy, others are trying to find out how to put small imperfect devices to work for solving real-world problem. A good overview of the quantum algorithm landscape.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org75dc8b2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org75dc8b2"&gt;Next-generation single-photon source for quantum information science - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-next-generation-single-photon-source-quantum-science.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org75dc8b2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science Advances - P. Kwiat (U. of Illinois), F. Kaneda (Tohoku U.)&lt;/i&gt; – Reliable single photon sources are extremely important for quantum communication, but hard to make. Using time multiplexing Kwiat's team managed to increase the efficiency of the process to the point where they could get several thousands of 12-photon events per second.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org085c97b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org085c97b"&gt;Quantum Threat Timeline - &lt;a href="https://globalriskinstitute.org/publications/quantum-threat-timeline/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org085c97b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;M Mosca and M Piani (EvolutionQ)&lt;/i&gt; – Research report published by the Global Risk Institute, trying to assess the quantum threat over classic cryptosystems. About 50% of the experts think that quantum computers will be threat for the current cryptosystems within 15 years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgde7e025" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgde7e025"&gt;Tracking Entanglement in a Quantum Simulator - &lt;a href="https://www.osa-opn.org/home/newsroom/2018/april/tracking_entanglement_in_a_quantum_simulator/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgde7e025"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Optics &amp;amp; Photonics - IQOQI (Innsbruck)&lt;/i&gt; – Report on a 20-qubit trapped ions experiment and the difficulty to know if a quantum device is behaving properly. Using a brute force approach would be equivalent to simulate the evolution of the quantum systems classically: fairly inefficient. By using the right (cryptographic) setting and tools, you can manage to do this much more efficiently.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdbd7801" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgdbd7801"&gt;New Encryption System Protects Data from Quantum Computers - &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/new-encryption-system-protects-data-from-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgdbd7801"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IBM Research Zurich - Vadim Lyubashevsky&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum algorithms are moving the world! The impact of algorithms not yet implemented shook the crypto community when the NIST asked in 2016 for new quantum-safe crytosystems to be proposed for a public release in 2024. IBM is reporting on their proposal called CRYSTALS that should be implemented in its cloud solutions by 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1b0eab5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1b0eab5"&gt;Cryptography without using secret keys - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-cryptography-secret-keys.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1b0eab5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. of Twente - W.r. Van Der Veen&lt;/i&gt; – Cryptography can make use of physically uncloneable functions for authentication and encryption. Here is a brief account about what this is and how it is done. Although there is a lot of quantum in there, the function (key in the article) is still classical. Quantum people have devised quantum attacks on such devices and also &lt;a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2019/1181"&gt;quantum PUF&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb69d9c0" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb69d9c0"&gt;Weaving quantum processors out of laser light - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-quantum-processors-laser.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb69d9c0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science DOI: 10.1126/science.aay2645 - Centre for Quantum Computation &amp;amp; Communication Technology, Nicolas Menicucci - U Tokyo - U New Mexico&lt;/i&gt; – The University of Melbourne CQC2T is reporting the creation of a large photonic cluster state. Cluster states are resources that can be used for implementing measurement based quantum computations. The nice thing is all the complicated stuff is made at the begining through the creation of this horribly entangled state. Using it is then much simpler as it requires only single qubit measurements and classically single qubit gates. This is quite an achievement and very motivating to see that fundamentally different architectures are subject of research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge2a58a4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge2a58a4"&gt;Blanket of light may give better quantum computers - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-blanket-quantum.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge2a58a4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science DOI: 10.1126/science.aay4354 - BigQ (Denmark), Ulrik Lund Andersen&lt;/i&gt;  – The Danes have done the same as the Aussies. Or is it the other way around. Impressive anyways: we are talking of 30 000 entangled light pulses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org5c0caf4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5c0caf4"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5c0caf4"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3337fc6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3337fc6"&gt;Barclays demonstrates proof-of-concept quantum clearing algorithm - &lt;a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/news/252472462/Barclays-demonstrates-proof-of-concept-quantum-clearing-algorithm"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3337fc6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Barclays, IBM&lt;/i&gt; – Looks like they have found a use for small scale quantum computer. Need to read the original &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.05788v1.pdf"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef1da0f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgef1da0f"&gt;Toshiba France advertises its QKD solution -  &lt;a href="https://www.toshiba.fr/?utm_source=cpc&amp;amp;utm_medium=linkedin&amp;amp;utm_campaign=fy19b&amp;amp;utm_content=qkd"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgef1da0f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Toshiba&lt;/i&gt; – Interesting to see industries picking up the subject. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge33ddae" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge33ddae"&gt;Rahko raises £1.3M seed from Balderton for quantum machine learning tech - &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/10/11/rahko-raises-1-3m-seed-from-balderton-for-quantum-machine-learning-tech/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge33ddae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rahko, Balderton Capital&lt;/i&gt; – Interesting to see a Series A VC fund invest in a seed round. VC's are probably seeing the quantum ecosystem as sufficiently small and the prospects with large corporations sufficiently interesting to make such unusual move. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org698427e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org698427e"&gt;IonQ Secures $55 Million in Funding to Bring Quantum Computing from the Lab to the Enterprise - &lt;a href="https://ionq.com/news/october-22-2019-new-funding"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org698427e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ -  Samsung Catalyst Fund and Mubadala Capital&lt;/i&gt; – $55m raised in this round, $77m total. That's serious money now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga701637" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga701637"&gt;Quantum photonics hardware developer Nu Quantum raises pre-seed investment - &lt;a href="https://www.amadeuscapital.com/quantum-photonics-hardware-developer-nu-quantum-raises-pre-seed-investment/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga701637"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nu Quantum, Amadeus Capital Partners, with participation from IQ Capital, Ahren Capital, Cambridge Enterprise and Martlet Capital&lt;/i&gt; – 650k pounds raised in a seed round for building single photon sources and detectors, which are the building blocks of quantum networks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3219fa6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3219fa6"&gt;Strathclyde quantum technology partnership secures £4.6 million - &lt;a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/whystrathclyde/news/strathclydequantumtechnologypartnershipsecures46million/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3219fa6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U Strathclyde - Msquared&lt;/i&gt; – A U Strathclyde + Msquared partnership secured funding worth a total of £4.6 million.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org8ccb6b4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8ccb6b4"&gt;HQS Quantum Simulations Closes €2.3 Million Seed Financing Round - &lt;a href="https://quantumsimulations.de/news/2019/10/hqs-closes-seed-financing-round/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8ccb6b4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;HQS Quantum Simulations&lt;/i&gt; – Designing software for quantum computer assisted material designs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4e1f29b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4e1f29b"&gt;Xanadu releases a nre quantum machine learning library for python - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pennylaneai/status/1186371620157493251?s=09"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4e1f29b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge25f12d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge25f12d"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge25f12d"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3603877" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3603877"&gt;Variational Fast Forwarding for Quantum Simulation Beyond the Coherence Time - &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04292"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3603877"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;LANL - Cristina Cirstoiu, Zoe Holmes, Joseph Iosue, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Andrew Sornborger&lt;/i&gt; – A new technique for simulating the evolution of quantum physical systems with noisy intermediate scale quantum computers that allows to go beyond the decoherence time of the quantum machines. Very cool!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1c159b0" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1c159b0"&gt;Learning the quantum algorithm for state overlap - &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1367-2630/aae94a/pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1c159b0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;LANL - Lukasz Cincio, Yiğit Subaş, Andrew T Sornborger and Patrick J Coles&lt;/i&gt; – Same group of people from Los Alamos. This one would help finding new circuits and serve as a guide for compiling high-level functions into device specific sequences of commands. Very promising (has led already to many follow-ups by the same group. Wondering how it can be adapted to make it work for optimizing communication protocols.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge040333" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge040333"&gt;Circuit-Based Quantum Random Access Memory for Classical Data - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-019-40439-3"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge040333"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;ITRC of Quantum Computing for AI, KAIST Korea - Daniel K. Park, Francesco Petruccione &amp;amp; June-Koo Kevin Rhee&lt;/i&gt; – Using quantum algorithms for solving real-world problems requires making classical data available to it. This paper describes a possible architecture for loading classical data into a quantum memory in an efficient way. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1267d99" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1267d99"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1267d99"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd464924" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd464924"&gt;PostDoc Positions at IQC (U. Waterloo) - &lt;a href="https://services.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/applications/positions/iqc-postdoctoral-fellowship/"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd464924"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IQC&lt;/i&gt; – Theory.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfe1457b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfe1457b"&gt;PostDoc Positions at IRIF (U. Paris) - &lt;a href="https://www.irif.fr/en/postes/postdoc"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfe1457b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IRIF&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum machine learning, optimization, quantum communications and cryptography.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org629f1d0" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org629f1d0"&gt;JQE Software internship at Rigetti - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rigetti/status/1186672593039847424?s=09"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org629f1d0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rigetti&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6708350" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6708350"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6708350"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb609d3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbb609d3"&gt;Quantum USA Vs. Quantum China: The World's Most Important Technology Race - &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/moorinsights/2019/10/10/quantum-usa-vs-quantum-china-the-worlds-most-important-technology-race/#135e818f72de"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbb609d3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Forbes&lt;/i&gt; –  US views on the investments by China into quantum technology.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgee73773" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgee73773"&gt;L'écosystème français de l'informatique quantique : ses atouts, ses faiblesses &lt;a href="https://www.latribune.fr/technos-medias/innovation-et-start-up/l-ecosysteme-francais-de-l-informatique-quantique-ses-atouts-ses-faiblesses-831271.html?utm_term=Autofeed&amp;amp;utm_medium=Social&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter#Echobox=1571760787"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgee73773"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;La Tribune&lt;/i&gt; – more or less accurate description of the french ecosystem. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org870f2d8" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org870f2d8"&gt;Quantum gold rush: the private funding pouring into quantum start-ups - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02935-4?utm_source=twt_nnc&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=naturenews&amp;amp;sf220597140=1"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org870f2d8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature doi: 10.1038/d41586-019-02935-4&lt;/i&gt; – 2017 and 2018 have seen 52 companies funded for $450m fresh money. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgcf1a20c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgcf1a20c"&gt;The hard sell of quantum software - &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/the-hard-sell-of-quantum-software/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgcf1a20c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;PhysicsWorld&lt;/i&gt; – Tries to explain why VCs invest in quantum software companies. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-24/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Breaking the breaking news... or not</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/breaking-the-breaking-news-or-not/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
In a paper posted today on arXiv &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.09534"&gt;1910.09534&lt;/a&gt;, a team of IBM scientists explain how Google's 53-qubit quantum computing supremacy experiment should only take 2.5 days to simulate on SUMMIT, Oak Ridge National Lab's supercomputer. Well, that's a quite a discrepency from Google's claim stating it would take over 10000 years to perform the computation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But what does it say about Google's supremacy claim in itself ? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First note that IBM is not arguing about the quantum computation Google's team has performed. They are arguing about the time required to perform an equivalent classical simulation using the world's most powerful supercomputer. Google said 10000 years, IBM – who happened to build the supercomputer – say 2.5 days if you optimize your computation using secondary storage. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This technique amounts to break up the classical simulation into pieces and off-loading non active parts to disk, while keeping the active ones in RAM. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here, what's important is that &lt;b&gt;IBM does not say they have found a better (i.e less complex) way to simulate Google's experiment, but a faster one&lt;/b&gt;. They are still doing about the same amount of exponential work. Their technique allows to lower the constant timing factors and in turn improve the compute time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, if you increase by just a few qubits the size of the quantum computation to be simulated, you are going back to the previous situation of a very long computation, because the dependency with the number of qubits is still exponential. The paper actually shows results for a 54-qubit quantum computation where the simulation time is at about 8 days. Hence, adding a single qubit more than doubles the time for simulating the experiment with 53 qubits: &lt;b&gt;still exponential&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While the debate about supremacy might live in the media, it is about the same as saying that the cost of electricity produced by renewable sources is at grid parity: it's a crossing point where economics are changing and pushing in favor of one source of energy over another. As for supremacy, the cost of electricity produced is also highly dependent on some hypotheses (e.g amortization rules), hence, it's more a benchmark than anything that you would rely on to do any serious investment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Talking about investment: SUMMIT was backed by a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summit_(supercomputer)"&gt;$325 millions contract&lt;/a&gt; and is taking 2.5 days to run a simulation that can be done in about 3min and a half on Google's machine. &lt;b&gt;Does it mean ORNL would have paid $325 billions for Google's machine?&lt;/b&gt; (yeah, 2.5 days is still about 1000 times longer than 3.5 minutes.)
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/breaking-the-breaking-news-or-not/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 11:58:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #4</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-04/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org9d91914" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9d91914"&gt;Breaking News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9d91914"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Google will be claiming quantum supremacy. It's a huge step for the field. A working intermediate scale QC at Google was able to perform a computation much faster than any available classical super-computer. Beware: I didn't say &lt;b&gt;any&lt;/b&gt; computation, but &lt;b&gt;a&lt;/b&gt; computation. I let you reflect on this. For more there is the excellent &lt;a href="https://www.scottaaronson.com/blog/?p=4317"&gt;Scott’s Supreme Quantum Supremacy FAQ!&lt;/a&gt;, and even more in Preskill's article in &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/john-preskill-explains-quantum-supremacy-20191002/"&gt;Quanta Magazine&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd826eca" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd826eca"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd826eca"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgba7340f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgba7340f"&gt;&lt;a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/observations/the-problem-with-quantum-computers/?amp;text=The"&gt;The Problem with Quantum Computers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgba7340f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Scientific American - Los Alamos National Lab&lt;/i&gt; – Decoherence is bad for quantum computing, but fortunately there are ways to fight it. Fault-tolerant gates are one of them. Optimized quantum circuits obtained via ML compilers are another. Here LANL researchers report using quantum computers to compile their own programs. Hey, we are getting away from low level assembly like code and circuits. Love it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org5cc0ad2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org5cc0ad2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/computer-scientists-expand-the-frontier-of-verifiable-knowledge-20190523/"&gt;Computer Scientists Expand the Frontier of Verifiable Knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org5cc0ad2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quanta magazine - Caltech - MIT&lt;/i&gt; – Using computers to verify that a solution given to a problem is exact is a common cryptographic setting. Think of digital signatures, its easy to check but without the private key you can't encode, i.e find the solution to the problem. When using quantum computers, you can verify efficiently the solutions to some of the hardest imaginable problems. Yay quantum!
&lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-04-method-enables-quantum-simulations-larger.html"&gt;New method enables quantum simulations on larger systems&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org - Science - U. Innsbruck&lt;/i&gt; – New method for characterizing multi-party states. That's one of the challenges (see subject above) of QC: know that your computer has been doing what it was supposed to do. Hey that's the experimentalists job augmented by the computer scientists approach. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org523f15a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org523f15a"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.frenchweb.fr/comprendre-linformatique-quantique-edition-2019-par-olivier-ezratty/376411"&gt;Comprendre l’informatique quantique&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org523f15a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;FrenchWeb - Olivier Ezratty&lt;/i&gt; – Incredible attemp by a non scientist to explain what quantum computing and quantum communication are. In french. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdd037f7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgdd037f7"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/stephanie-wehner-is-designing-a-quantum-internet-20190925/"&gt;To Invent a Quantum Internet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgdd037f7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quanta Magazine - Stephanie Wehner&lt;/i&gt; – What to know why Quantum Information Science is not Computing only ? Read this! LIP6 is taking care of the upper network layers with other embers of the Paris node. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B76dFHnGdLM"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B76dFHnGdLM&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org8940776" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8940776"&gt;&lt;a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2019-09-quantum-internet-closer-reality.html"&gt;Project brings quantum internet closer to reality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8940776"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;TechXplore - U Innsbruck - Army Research Lab&lt;/i&gt; – Sending entanglement over long distances (50km) successfully is a huge achievement, because not only do you need to create the entanglement, but you also need to convert the created photon pairs to telecom wavelength!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgee1c66d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgee1c66d"&gt;&lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2019/10/239668-closing-in-on-quantum-error-correction/fulltext"&gt;Closing In on Quantum Error Correction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgee1c66d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Communications of the ACM - IQC / PI&lt;/i&gt; – A short overview of what quantum error correction is and why it is useful (well the statement that nothing interesting can be done without it is raising debates). Some more cool stuff on Surface codes in the Research Paper section, where D. Poulin has been constructing wormholes in them. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org34ae54c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org34ae54c"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org34ae54c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you read till her, I asume you've heard about Google Supremacy Claim.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org79afa1f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org79afa1f"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org79afa1f"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org74bbff2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org74bbff2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.07419"&gt;Topological wormholes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org74bbff2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Sherbrooke - A. Krishna, D. Poulin&lt;/i&gt; – Having fun with toric codes, puncturing and stiching. It's a novel way to do fault tolerant computation using toric codes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgce86523" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgce86523"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/0602130"&gt;One-and-a-half quantum de Finetti theorems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgce86523"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Matthias Christandl, Robert Koenig, Graeme Mitchison, Renato Renner, Approximations of the de Finetti theorem when there are finitely many systems&lt;/i&gt; – Not a recent one, but a good one. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9dc167d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9dc167d"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1209.0448"&gt;A classical leash for a quantum system: Command of quantum systems via rigidity of CHSH games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9dc167d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Ben W. Reichardt, Falk Unger, Umesh Vazirani&lt;/i&gt; – Another important one for caracterizing geometric properties of entangled states… giving them some rigidity properties.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc1c4bc4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc1c4bc4"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc1c4bc4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/romain-all%C3%A9aume-0778066_postdoc-announcement-activity-6580134490172084224-dPIz/"&gt;Telecom Paris is looking for a PostDoc&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Telecom Paris&lt;/i&gt; – Will be on experimental quantum coherent communications.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc5360c9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc5360c9"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc5360c9"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd4c6247" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd4c6247"&gt;&lt;a href="https://popl20.sigplan.org/home/planqc-2020"&gt;PLanQC 2020 Programming Languages for Quantum Computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd4c6247"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Submission deadline 2019-10-28&lt;/i&gt; - Event on 2020-01-20/ – One day workshop around languages and tools for quantum computer coding.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6a3d2f3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6a3d2f3"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6a3d2f3"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org28c3229" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org28c3229"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLgLkEJ3SUJUS05I_INGLpkNcaWQdXfCeo&amp;amp;app=desktop"&gt;Slides from the Fifth International Conference on Quantum Error Correction (QEC’19)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgafa7873" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgafa7873"&gt;&lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-09-car-math.html"&gt;Where to park your car, according to math&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgafa7873"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Santa Fe Institute - Boston U&lt;/i&gt; – Use this whenever you need to explain what algorithm and optimization is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-04/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 04:32:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #3</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-09-18/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org3724a8e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org3724a8e"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org3724a8e"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org825ae37" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org825ae37"&gt;&lt;a href="https://qutech.nl/fully-controllable-and-highly-stable-10-qubit-chip-paves-way-for-larger-quantum-processo/"&gt;Fully controllable and highly stable 10-qubit chip paves way for larger quantum processor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org825ae37"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;QuTech, TU Delft, TNO&lt;/i&gt; – Showing entanglement between all possible qubit pairs, ability to generate 7 qubits entanglement, and 1min decoherence time. That's super-long. Looking forward to see larger registers, and also how these can be used to serve as quantum repeaters in networks.
Some additional info at &lt;a href="https://physics.aps.org/synopsis-for/10.1103/PhysRevX.9.031045"&gt;physics.aps.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd032a4e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd032a4e"&gt;&lt;a href="https://csferrie.com/2019/09/09/quantum-entanglement-for-toddlers/"&gt;Quantum Entanglement for Toddlers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd032a4e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don't talk to me if you haven't read this. It you have but mix-up entanglement and correlations well, you'll be roasted :-)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge96289a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge96289a"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge96289a"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4717242" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4717242"&gt;&lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/digital-single-market/en/news/new-quantum-project-aims-ultra-secure-communication-europe"&gt;New quantum project aims for ultra-secure communication in Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4717242"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Europe&lt;/i&gt; – Europe is launching OPENQKD and initiative to test quantum communications in several european countries: Hungary, Portugal, Poland, Belgium, Germany, Italy, Luxembourg, Malta, the Netherlands, and Spain. The important part is not QKD but quantum communication. QKD will be a test not the single final outcome of the initiative. Just saying this to all other Member states where people see QKD as the only thing to do with quantum networks. Well have a look at the quantum protocol zoo &lt;a href="http://wiki.veriqloud.fr"&gt;http://wiki.veriqloud.fr&lt;/a&gt;. By the way, where is France in this list ?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org83b1b21" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org83b1b21"&gt;&lt;a href="https://q-ctrl.com/blog/global-vc-bets-on-sydney-quantum-computing-start-up-q-ctrl-in-us15m-series-a/"&gt;Global VC Bets on Sydney Quantum Computing Start-up Q-CTRL in US$15M Series A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org83b1b21"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Q-CTRL, Square Peg Capital, Sequoia Capital, Main Sequence Ventures, Horizons Venture, Sierra Ventures&lt;/i&gt; – Provides firmware for quantum computing hardware with the goal to reduce decoherence and errors. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdc6d84c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgdc6d84c"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fraunhofer.de/en/press/research-news/2019/september/ibm-and-fraunhofer-team-up-to-promote-quantum-computing-in-europe.html"&gt;IBM and Fraunhofer team up to promote quantum computing in Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgdc6d84c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IBM-Q, Fraunhofer&lt;/i&gt; – 650m euros on the table for quantum computer. Germany also has partnerships with Google. Looks like a coordinated public effort is made to attract the best minds and projects to Germany.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgddd7ccb" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgddd7ccb"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/qc-ware-hires-leading-minds-in-quantum-computing-to-build-algorithms-that-will-power-the-next-evolution-in-computing-300916555.html?=lve"&gt;QC Ware Hires Leading Minds in Quantum Computing to Build Algorithms that will Power the Next Evolution in Computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgddd7ccb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;QCWare, Scott Aaronson&lt;/i&gt; – QCWare hires Scott Aaronson. They will have one of the strongest team in the world with Win van Dam, Iordanis Kerenidis and now Scott.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4a1066f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4a1066f"&gt;&lt;a href="https://nachrichten.idw-online.de/2019/09/16/quantum-computers-by-aqt-and-university-of-innsbruck-leverage-cirq-for-quantum-algorithm-development/"&gt;Quantum computers by AQT and University of Innsbruck use Google Cirq language for quantum algorithm development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4a1066f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Google, U. Innsbruck, AQT&lt;/i&gt; – Cirq is Google's quantum programming language, that's not only used for sending commands to Google's quantum computers but also to AQT and U. Innsbruck ones.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfc00cd1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfc00cd1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://newsroom.ibm.com/2019-09-18-IBM-Opens-Quantum-Computation-Center-in-New-York-Brings-Worlds-Largest-Fleet-of-Quantum-Computing-Systems-Online-Unveils-New-53-Qubit-Quantum-System-for-Broad-Use"&gt;IBM-Q annonces a 53 qubits quantum computer available next month&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfc00cd1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IBM-Q&lt;/i&gt; – 14 systems will be commercially available with one being a 53 qubits universal quantum computer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7c13885" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7c13885"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7c13885"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7cec306" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7cec306"&gt;MIT is hiring a &lt;a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/14310"&gt;physics assistant professor&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/14428"&gt;postdoc&lt;/a&gt; both to work on quantum information and quantum computing.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7cec306"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;MIT&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org454dd22" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org454dd22"&gt;&lt;a href="https://academicjobsonline.org/ajo/jobs/14493"&gt;QuICS is looking for Hartree Postdoctoral fellowships&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org454dd22"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;NIST&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org35d4db6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org35d4db6"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iqoqi-vienna.at/research/yirg-young-independent-researcher-group"&gt;Institute for Quantum Optics and Quantum Information (IQOQI) is looking for a PhD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org35d4db6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IQOQI&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org37abc34" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org37abc34"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org37abc34"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga8da861" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga8da861"&gt;&lt;a href="https://physicstoday.scitation.org/do/10.1063/PT.6.4.20190911a/full/"&gt;Author Q&amp;amp;A: How to write a graphic novel about quantum mechanics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga8da861"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Physics Today&lt;/i&gt; – How to write and draw general public books on quantum mechanics… ?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-09-18/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 04:32:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #2</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-09-09/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org814c9a8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org814c9a8"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org814c9a8"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb6f792a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb6f792a"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www-technologyreview-com.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/www.technologyreview.com/s/614160/quantum-radar-has-been-demonstrated-for-the-first-time/amp"&gt;Quantum radar has been demonstrated for the first time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb6f792a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;MIT Tech Review&lt;/i&gt; – Some by-products of quantum communication could be linking arrays of detectors together: Quantum radar is one such by-product.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7158907" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7158907"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=2&amp;amp;v=X-lrQt_UxxQ"&gt;La seconde révolution quantique et l'ordinateur de Sissa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7158907"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;TEDx, Quantum Flagship, Philippe Chomaz&lt;/i&gt; – For the french speaking an brief intro to quantumm computing by Quantum Flagship member P. Chomaz.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgac59341" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgac59341"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.icfo.es/newsroom/news/article/4495"&gt;Quantum Memories make their way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgac59341"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;ICFO&lt;/i&gt; – Reports on progress of quantum memories and repeaters. Two major intgredients needed for sending quantum information in quantum networks and allow for local computation at the nodes.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org66da5af" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org66da5af"&gt;&lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/quantum-darwinism-spotted-in-diamond-spins/"&gt;Quantum Darwinism spotted in diamond spins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org66da5af"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Ulm&lt;/i&gt; – People testing ideas I developped with Wojciech Zurek at LANL about 20 yrs ago. Feeling honored that people are spending time checking in real life what you have written on a piece of paper. Some more in a podcast from physics world &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/survival-of-the-fittest-quantum-states-scrutinizing-antihydrogen-physics-of-chilled-drinks/"&gt;https://physicsworld.com/a/survival-of-the-fittest-quantum-states-scrutinizing-antihydrogen-physics-of-chilled-drinks/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org25db961" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org25db961"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/sap/2019/09/04/why-quantum-computers-wont-replace-classical-computers-anytime-soon/#7c432f68136a"&gt;Why Quantum Computers Won’t Replace Classical Computers Anytime Soon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org25db961"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Forbes&lt;/i&gt; – Always good to be aware of hype in an area. Interesting bit (at the end) partnership of SAP and Quantum Internet Alliance for undertanding what the future of computing will be, and also the need for the new generations of developpers to know some more algorithmics and linear algebra.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2cd9a90" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2cd9a90"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2cd9a90"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7d8d12e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7d8d12e"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/qctrlHQ/status/1168332684017274880"&gt;Q-CTRL joins IBM-Q partner list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7d8d12e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Q-CTRL - Sidney, IBM-Q&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf3c7706" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf3c7706"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/news/ibm-quantum-computing-services-education,40329.html"&gt;IBM Launches New Services for Quantum Computing Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf3c7706"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IBM-Q&lt;/i&gt; – Some continued effort in making quantum computation available in the classroom, to motivate and teach the skills that will be required for people wanting to work in the field.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org38ed6f1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org38ed6f1"&gt;Qnami enters the Top100 Swiss start-ups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org38ed6f1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Qnami, Switzerland&lt;/i&gt; – quantum microscope, surface analysis, NV diamonds
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd5d9543" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd5d9543"&gt;&lt;a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/quantum/2017/12/11/announcing-microsoft-quantum-development-kit/"&gt;Announcing the Microsoft Quantum Development Kit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd5d9543"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – full integration of Q# within visual studio, local and Azure simulators, open-source libraries: quantum race ? definitely open-source oriented at least which helps circulating ideas and designs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgee13323" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgee13323"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgee13323"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgaa45849" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgaa45849"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1908.08069.pdf"&gt;Closing gaps of a quantum advantage with short-time Hamiltonian dynamics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgaa45849"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Jonas Haferkamp, Dominik Hangleiter, Adam Bouland, Bill Fefferman, Jens Eisert, and Juani Bermejo-Vega&lt;/i&gt; – 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd1e6aa5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd1e6aa5"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42254-018-0003-5.pdf"&gt;Entanglement certification from theory to experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd1e6aa5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nicolai Friis,  Giuseppe Vitagliano, Mehul Malik, and Marcus Huber&lt;/i&gt; – Long but really useful with a very complete bibliography.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org21a1c32" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org21a1c32"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/9604024"&gt;Mixed State Entanglement and Quantum Error Correction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org21a1c32"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Charles H. Bennett, David P. DiVincenzo, John A. Smolin and William K. Wootters&lt;/i&gt; – Guess what I'm interested in distillation protocols.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdec4353" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdec4353"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdec4353"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7536474" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7536474"&gt;2 year Postdoc at Griffith U.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7536474"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Griffith U.&lt;/i&gt; – The Centre for Quantum Dynamics at Griffith University is offering a 2-year Postdoctoral Research Fellow position in quantum foundations. The Research Fellow will be funded by, and expected to contribute to, two externally-funded research projects led by Dr Eric Cavalcanti: Australian Research Council Future Fellowship “Fine-tuning the quantum: foundations and applications of quantum causality” and Foundational Questions Institute Large Grant “Causal reasoning in quantum agents”.  The successful applicant will have a PhD in Physics, Mathematics, Computer Science, Philosophy, or related fields, and may contribute to these projects through conceptual, analytical or numerical work, depending on the applicant’s background and interests. The position is also required to undertake higher degree research supervision.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org441c594" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org441c594"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org441c594"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org40897e2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org40897e2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.co/yrRzXIsTHW"&gt;Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org40897e2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Daejon, South Korea, oct 22-24&lt;/i&gt; – speakers from Google, Microsoft, IBM, Rigetti, … 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbdf1f9c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbdf1f9c"&gt;&lt;a href="https://labs.ripe.net/Members/ulka_athale_1/take-part-in-pan-european-quantum-internet-hackathon"&gt;First Pan-European Quantum Hackathon (nov 5 - 6, Paris)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbdf1f9c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Paris, Delft, Dublin, Padua, Sarajevo&lt;/i&gt; – As part of the Paris Node, LIP6 is co-organizing the hackathon with other research instutions, members of the industry and investors. We will be happy to welcome you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-09-09/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 04:32:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #1</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-08-30/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org80547a1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org80547a1"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org80547a1"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd650920" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd650920"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-quantum-internet-is-emerging-one-experiment-at-a-time/"&gt;The Quantum Internet Is Emerging, One Experiment at a Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd650920"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Scientific american&lt;/i&gt; – Explains the motivations, challenges and main options taken by research groups working on the quantum internet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgac9dfd7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgac9dfd7"&gt;&lt;a href="https://m.phys.org/news/2019-07-breakthrough-quantum.html"&gt;Researchers lead breakthrough in quantum computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgac9dfd7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Virginia Tech College&lt;/i&gt; – Efficient quantum algorithms for computing molecular properties.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org03fb596" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org03fb596"&gt;&lt;a href="https://m.phys.org/news/2019-08-entanglement-km-optical-fiber.html"&gt;Entanglement sent over 50 km of optical fiber&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org03fb596"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Innsbruck&lt;/i&gt; – Report of creating and sharing a entangled pair of photons at telecom wavelength (1550nm) for over 50km. This is one of the major requirement needed for a functional quantum network.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org57b2147" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org57b2147"&gt;&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/dI-JW2UIAG0"&gt;How did NASA Steer the Saturn V?- Smarter Every Day 223&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org57b2147"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Want to understand what the fate of quantum computers is with respect to error correction? Watch this! For controlling Satrun V, the computation was run in parallel on 2 computers ; for quantum computation you need to run it in a parallel encoded version (a logical qubit made of many physical ones) to achieve the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb1ff656" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb1ff656"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb1ff656"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7418390" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7418390"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ehu.eus/en/web/campusa-magazine/-/upv-ehu-is-one-of-the-european-leading-institutions-partnering-with-ibm-to-accelerate-quantum-computing"&gt;UPV/EHU is one of the European leading institutions partnering with IBM to accelerate quantum computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7418390"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;UPV EHU - IBM Q&lt;/i&gt; – IBMQ announces research and educations partnerships with Aalto University, University of Turku, EPFL, University of the Basque Country and The International Iberian Nanotechnology Laboratory.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org22c5286" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org22c5286"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ehu.eus/en/web/campusa-magazine/-/upv-ehu-is-one-of-the-european-leading-institutions-partnering-with-ibm-to-accelerate-quantum-computing"&gt;Europe’s VCs finally leap into quantum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org22c5286"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Spin-off Aalo - IQM&lt;/i&gt; – IQM (super-conducting qubits) got 11.45m euros in a VC investment round.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgebd3385" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgebd3385"&gt;&lt;a href="https://m.phys.org/news/2019-07-breakthrough-quantum.html"&gt;Stonybrook U and BNL to develop a quantum network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgebd3385"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;BNL - Stonybrook U.&lt;/i&gt; – Long distance network testbed for open air photonic quantum network.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7d2f685" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7d2f685"&gt;&lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/big-stuff-with-little-qubits/"&gt;Big stuff with little qubits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7d2f685"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Zurich Instruments&lt;/i&gt; – A startup supplying instruments for people measuring spins (from NMR to superconducting qubits).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0c4b13c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0c4b13c"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0c4b13c"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9405823" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9405823"&gt;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.09415"&gt;Ronald de Wolf lecture notes on quantum computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org55c6bbf" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org55c6bbf"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org55c6bbf"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org51bf771" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org51bf771"&gt;2 Postdocs ar UMD / LPS on NISQ and QML&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org51bf771"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;UMD LPS&lt;/i&gt; – &lt;a href="https://t.co/cHehDmkpEV"&gt;https://t.co/cHehDmkpEV&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org8c4d6eb" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8c4d6eb"&gt;Tenures at university of Amsterdam&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8c4d6eb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Amsterdam&lt;/i&gt; – &lt;a href="https://t.co/aPZB1cXdsI"&gt;https://t.co/aPZB1cXdsI&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2e4d956" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2e4d956"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2e4d956"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb60f557" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb60f557"&gt;&lt;a href="https://quantumfrontiers.com/2019/07/15/tiqtaqtoe/"&gt;Releasing a quantum version of TiqTaqToe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb60f557"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Caltech&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-08-30/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 04:32:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>