<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Qoherences</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/</link><description>News for quantum people</description><atom:link href="https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:harold.ollivier@linksights.io"&gt;Harold Ollivier&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 05:23:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>EuroCrypt 2020: Quantum program</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/20200511/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
EuroCrypt 2020 going virtual, mst talks are available from the website of conference (sending back to IACR &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCV-WittrGkRyONzX6UmCaiA"&gt;youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org3e398e6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org3e398e6"&gt;Quantum Cryptography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org3e398e6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moderators: Zvika Brakerski, Anne Broadbent, and Adam Smith
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure-Rewind-Measure: Tighter Quantum Random Oracle Model Proofs for One-Way to Hiding and CCA Security (&lt;i&gt;Veronika Kuchta Amin Sakzad Damien Stehlé Ron Steinfeld Shi-Feng Sun&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secure Multi-party Quantum Computation with a Dishonest Majority (&lt;i&gt;Yfke Dulek Stacey Jeffery Alex B. Grilo Christian Majenz Christian Schaffner&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficient Simulation of Random States and Random Unitaries (&lt;i&gt;Gorjan Alagic Christian Majenz Alexander Russell&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum-Access-Secure Message Authentication via Blind-Unforgeability (&lt;i&gt;Gorjan Alagic Christian Majenz Alexander Russell Fang Song&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc823d63" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc823d63"&gt;Quantum Cryptanalysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc823d63"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moderators: Jian Guo, Gregor Leander, Bart Mennik, and Gilles Van Assche
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding Hash Collisions with Quantum Computers by Using Differential Trails with Smaller Probability than Birthday Bound (&lt;i&gt;Akinori Hosoyamada Yu Sasaki&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing Grover oracles for quantum key search on AES and LowMC (&lt;i&gt;Samuel Jaques Michael Naehrig Martin Roetteler Fernando Virdia&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimal Merging in Quantum $k$-xor and $k$-sum Algorithms (&lt;i&gt;María Naya-Plasencia André Schrottenloher&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Quantum Complexity of the Continuous Hidden Subgroup Problem (&lt;i&gt;Koen de Boer Léo Ducas Serge Fehr&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/20200511/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 05:03:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quantum Papers at Eurocrypt 2020</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-04-27/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://eurocrypt.iacr.org/2020/"&gt;Eurocrypt&lt;/a&gt; is one major conference in cryptography and secure computing. This year it will go virtual may 11-15. As usual it will have a few (good) talks on quantum. I've already seen "Secure Multi-party Quantum Computation with a Dishonest Majority" it's a nice one!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The final program hasn't been released yet. The page will be updated then.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimal Merging in Quantum k-xor and k-sum Algorithms
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;María Naya-Plasencia (Inria, France); André Schrottenloher (Inria, France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing Grover oracles for quantum key search on AES and LowMC
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samuel Jaques (Department of Materials, University of Oxford, UK); Michael Naehrig (Microsoft Research, Redmond, USA); Martin Roetteler (Microsoft Quantum, Redmond, USA); Fernando Virdia (Information Security Group, Royal Holloway, University of London, UK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Quantum Complexity of the Continuous Hidden Subgroup Problem
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Koen de Boer (Cryptology Group, CWI, Amsterdam, The Netherlands); Léo Ducas (Cryptology Group, CWI, Amsterdam, The Netherlands); Serge Fehr (Cryptology Group, CWI, Amsterdam, The Netherlands and Mathematical Institute, Leiden University, The Netherlands)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secure Multi-party Quantum Computation with a Dishonest Majority
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yfke Dulek (QuSoft and U. Amsterdam); Alex B. Grilo (QuSoft and CWI); Stacey Jeffery (QuSoft and CWI); Christian Majenz (QuSoft and CWI); Christian Schaffner (QuSoft and U. Amsterdam)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum Security Analysis of CSIDH
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xavier Bonnetain (Inria, France); André Schrottenloher (Inria, France)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fractal: Post-Quantum and Transparent Recursive Proofs from Holography
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alessandro Chiesa (UC Berkeley); Dev Ojha (UC Berkeley); Nicholas Spooner (UC Berkeley)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding Hash Collisions with Quantum Computers by Using Differential Trails with Smaller Probability than Birthday Bound
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Akinori Hosoyamada (NTT Secure Platform Laboratories and Nagoya University); Yu Sasaki (NTT Secure Platform Laboratories)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measure-Rewind-Measure: Tighter Quantum Random Oracle Model Proofs for One-Way to Hiding Lemma and CCA Security
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veronika Kuchta (Monash University, Australia); Amin Sakzad (Monash University, Australia); Damien Stehlé (ENS de Lyon, France); Ron Steinfeld (Monash University, Australia); Shi-Feng Sun (Monash University and Data61, CSIRO, Australia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum-access-secure message authentication via blind-unforgeability
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gorjan Alagic (QuICS, University of Maryland, and NIST, Gaithersburg, Maryland); Christian Majenz (QuSoft and CWI, Amsterdam, The Netherlands); Alexander Russell (Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University of Connecticut); Fang Song (Texas A&amp;amp;M University)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://eurocrypt.iacr.org/2020/registration.php"&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-04-27/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 07:53:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quantum Advantage with Shallow Circuits - Sergey Bravyi</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-04-25/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
As part of the Qiskit Channel, IBM hosted on 2020-04-24 a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uwZjUI5eKAk"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; by Sergey Bravyi on achieving Quantum Advantage with Shallow Depth Circuits. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's starts with a through and step by step introduction to the problem and its importance. First by stating necessary conditions for a good definition of quantum advantage. It needs to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have an efficient quantum circuit implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be classically hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be verifiable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While verifiability has always been a concern to people working in the field, it is interesting to see it deeply rooted in Sergey's requirements. Verifiability allows an experimentalist to convince skeptics that he has done a computation that is really solving the problem he stated. That's not obvious as a skeptic could not run a classical computation to check the result! Other models such as VUBQC offer built-in verifiability but we are not yet able to implement these models with the current devices (although photonics looks promising in this respect).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a side remark Sergey made it clear that the problem solved need not be of practical interest. It just needs to be hard to solve classically.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The nice surprise is to discover that the result indeed relies on a generalization of the Magic Square Game of Peres and Mermin. The idea is to have a play of the game between Alice and Bob placed at random positions in a quantum register. The other positions would use entanglement swapping to help them solve the game with probability 1. All this can be performed in constant depth (in the number of possible location available / register size). On the other hand, if we play the same game but with access to classical circuits only, because one would need the strategy to work for all positions of Alice and Bob, in a situation where the size of the register increases, it is possible to show that you need logarithmic depth circuits. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a very nice result that appeared in Science 362 p308 (2018), and I think the setting also hints at the advantage of small scale quantum computers in entanglement routing networks. 
&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-04-25/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 07:06:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #8</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-02-04/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Lets start with a call from last year published in Nature that I find particularly important: &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02675-5"&gt;Keep quantum computing global and open&lt;/a&gt;! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc03354e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc03354e"&gt;General Public Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc03354e"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1d3b4e5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1d3b4e5"&gt;Computer Scientists Expand the Frontier of Verifiable Knowledge – &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/computer-scientists-expand-the-frontier-of-verifiable-knowledge-20190523/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1d3b4e5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quanta Magazine – MIT, Caltech&lt;/i&gt; – Very nice account on a work that emphasizes the questions raised by tapping into resources (quantum computers) to give you answers to problems that you don't know the answer of. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2cdffac" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2cdffac"&gt;New algorithms to determine eigenstates and thermal states on quantum computers – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-algorithms-eigenstates-thermal-states-quantum.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2cdffac"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature – CalTech&lt;/i&gt; – New algorithms (quantum imaginary time)  useful to estimate properties of ground states and thermal states of quantum materials.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2af20af" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2af20af"&gt;Photonic quantum information processing: A concise review – &lt;a href="https://aip.scitation.org/doi/10.1063/1.5115814"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2af20af"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;AIP&lt;/i&gt; – Review of the photonic path towards scalable fault tolerant QC.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org512c06d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org512c06d"&gt;First chip-to-chip quantum teleportation harnessing silicon photonic chip fabrication – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-12-chip-to-chip-quantum-teleportation-harnessing-silicon.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org512c06d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org – U Bristol, DTU&lt;/i&gt; – A milestone achieved in regard to building optical chips for quantum information processing and networking. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0c26681" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0c26681"&gt;In leap for quantum computing, silicon quantum bits establish a long-distance relationship – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-12-quantum-silicon-bits-long-distance-relationship.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0c26681"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org – U Princeton&lt;/i&gt; – Enabling quantum gates between silicon spin qubits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org65e68b1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org65e68b1"&gt;In surprise breakthrough, scientists create quantum states in everyday electronics – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-12-breakthrough-scientists-quantum-states-everyday.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org65e68b1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org – U Chicago&lt;/i&gt; – Not quite everyday's electronic, but quantum dots in silicon carbide. Interesting advances anyways.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdf59375" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdf59375"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdf59375"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd9fe23a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd9fe23a"&gt;Russia joins the quantum race – &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03855-z"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd9fe23a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature – Russia&lt;/i&gt; – Russia plans to spend several hundred millions of dollars to boost its quantum information science and technology capabilities. There remains to see which institutes and labs will be receiving the money as the academic and start-up ecosystem is not much developed yet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf5770c1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf5770c1"&gt;Israel Gets Ready to Join Global Quantum Computing Race – &lt;a href="https://www.haaretz.com/israel-news/business/.premium-israel-gets-ready-to-join-global-quantum-computing-race-1.8202806"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf5770c1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Haaretz – Israel&lt;/i&gt; – 350m$ over 6 years in funding. Quite a lot. A small country with plenty of excellent quantum teams to spend the money on. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org44a89a6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org44a89a6"&gt;Nine More EU States Commit To Building A Quantum Communication Infrastructure – &lt;a href="https://www.cbronline.com/news/quantum-communication-infrastructure"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org44a89a6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;CBR&lt;/i&gt; – Croatia, Cyprus, Greece, France, Lithuania, Slovakia, Slovenia, Sweden and Finland are the newest members entering into agreement that will see them work with ten EU states to establish a quantum communication infrastructure across Europe.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0585d68" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0585d68"&gt;Xanadu Receives $4.4M Investment from SDTC to Advance its Photonic Quantum Computing Technology – &lt;a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/xanadu-receives-4-4m-investment-from-sdtc-to-advance-its-photonic-quantum-computing-technology-300987885.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0585d68"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;prnewswire – Xanadu, SDTC&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge30990c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge30990c"&gt;OpenQKD Fuels European Quantum Computing Research, Potential in Aerospace – &lt;a href="https://www.aviationtoday.com/2019/12/02/openqkd-fuels-european-quantum-computing-research-potential-aerospace/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge30990c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Avionics – Airbus, Thales, U. Paris Sorbonne, U. Paris Saclay&lt;/i&gt; – Launching the OpenQKD project aimed at QKD mostly for open air / satellite communication and sensing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6be3f1c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6be3f1c"&gt;University of Chicago's Tian Zhong awarded NSF grant to create quantum internet – &lt;a href="https://www.quantaneo.com/University-of-Chicago-s-Tian-Zhong-Awarded-NSF-Grant-to-Create-Quantum-Internet_a407.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6be3f1c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quantaneo – U. Chicago&lt;/i&gt; – The US are catching up with Europe on quantum internet initiatives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge630c1e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge630c1e"&gt;Atos partners with Zapata to deliver complete quantum computing solution to the enterprise – &lt;a href="https://www.quantaneo.com/Atos-partners-with-Zapata-to-deliver-complete-quantum-computing-solution-to-the-enterprise_a333.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge630c1e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quantaneo – Atos, Zapata&lt;/i&gt; – Addressing vertical markets is key to adoption of quantum technologies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga5a0060" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga5a0060"&gt;Goldman Sachs enlists startup for quantum computing push – &lt;a href="https://www.finextra.com/newsarticle/34941/goldman-sachs-enlists-startup-for-quantum-computing-push"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga5a0060"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Finextra – Goldman Sachs, QC Ware&lt;/i&gt; – More and more exploration of QC algorithms for finance. These are appalling use cases for quantum computing start-ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org93170e6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org93170e6"&gt;What It Will Take to Make Quantum Computers Practical – &lt;a href="https://newsroom.intel.com/editorials/what-it-will-take-make-quantum-computers-practical/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org93170e6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Intel&lt;/i&gt; – Intel pushes its efforts toward control of qubits. Very much needed indeed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2020-02-04/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 04:48:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reading QIP's papers (Part I)</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/reading_qip_papers/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org7900f4e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7900f4e"&gt;Dequantizing quantum machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7900f4e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the highlights of QIP2020 was Ewin Tang's presentation of her dequantization technique. It was an overview of the work she has been doing since july 2018. I would highly recommend her blog &lt;a href="https://ewintang.com/blog/2019/01/28/an-overview-of-quantum-inspired-sampling/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; as a first introduction. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To summarize the topic even further, till then, QML had access to an unfair assumption (efficient state vector preparation from classical data). The first part of Ewin Tang's work is to find the proper definition of a similar and comparable assumption for classical problems which is called "sample-query". Then she shows that under such assumption, you can perform 3 subroutines efficiently:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inner product of two complex vectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thin matrix-vector simulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;low-rank approximation of a matrix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This makes the core of her work: within the sample-query assumption, you can perform randomized numerical linear algebra efficiently. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The rest follows by replacing in quantum algorithms access to quantum evolution and sampling by the efficient classical subroutines above. This applies to supervised clustering, recommendation systems and low-rank matrix inversion.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org79daaba" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org79daaba"&gt;Predicting features of quantum systems from very few measurements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org79daaba"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we want to verify that an experiment worked the way it was supposed to, the usual approach is to perform state tomography. This means measuring a complete set of observables, estimate each of them accurately and reconstructing the quantum state from there. While this sounds very natural, it is usually overkill for what we &lt;b&gt;really&lt;/b&gt; want to do. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In fact, nmost of the time, we are interested not in the actual state of the quantum system, but only in predicting the outcome of certain measurements on this system. This happens when we can estimate the fidelity of the state to another pure state to show that the experiment produced almost the state is was supposed to produce. In such case, once we know that the state vector is almost at the right position, because the density matrix is positive semi definite and with trace 1, it's not  necessary to measure the other coefficients of the matrix anymore. We know they are small. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are various ways of optimizing the number of measurements to perform these kind of tasks. The one presented in this &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1908.08909"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; works in the following way: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realize that measuring your state in the computational basis after applying to it a random Clifford circuit is equivalent to perform the POVM where each POVM element is a projector onto a stabilizer state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stabilizer states form a 3-design, i.e they can evaluate exactly any probability measure on the \(n\) qubit pure states up to the third moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
1 and 2 give that if the POVM element associated to the stabilizer state \(|s\rangle\) was obtained in the measurement, \(\hat \rho = (2^n+1) |s\rangle\langle s| - Id\) is a good estimator of \(\text{tr}(O\rho)\) where \(O\) is hermitian.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, we get a good convergence by repeating these measurements \(N\) times and using median of means estimation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The main theorem then follows: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Suppose \(\rho\) is the state of a system composed of \(n\) qubits. Take \(N\) copies of this system. Fix \(\{O_i\}_{i\ in \[M\]}\) be \(M\) hermitian matrices of size \(2^n \times 2^n\). Set \(\epsilon\) and \(\delta\) in \(\[0,1\]\). Then \(N = 204 \log(2M/\delta) \max_i \tr(O_i^2)/\epsilon^2\) is sufficient to predict all function evaluations of \(\tr O_i\rho\) within \(\epsilon\) with probability at least \(1-\delta\) via measurement of random clifford circuits and median of means estimation. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/reading_qip_papers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 05:27:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Highlights from QIP2020</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/highlights_from_qip/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org77d9ef5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org77d9ef5"&gt;Stats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org77d9ef5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Quantum Information Processing 2020 is the 23rd edition of this major conference for the field. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The conference was a big success both in terms of attendence and science (more on that below). Just to give a few stats shared by the organizing committees: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were more than 700 participants (Industry ~100, Students ~300, Senior Scientists ~300)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not surprisingly attendance was skewed towards Chinese participants (~400). However compared to the previous edition in China (Beijin 2013, 140 Chinese participants) that's a huge increase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 70 talks have been scheduled covering most of quantum information processing subjects from a theoretical perspective (Quantum algorithms, complexity, error correction and protection, fault tolerance, resource theory, testing / verification / certification, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A considerable number (350) of posters have been presented making it hard to find the ones that were in your subfield.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An industry session was organized showcasing the work done by local companies (Baidu, Huawei, Alibaba, SpinQ, CAS Quantum Net, Quantum CTek)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just a few observations from here: QIP has a very broad coverage of the field. As such it is very open and worthwhile attending as speakers tend to make an effort to present their subject after some general motivation / context description. It would be a hard take for purely experimental physicists, but theoreticians working on experiments should definitely attend (more) especially error correction sessions, some algorithm talks as well as some certification / verification ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now the scientific part!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org8762950" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8762950"&gt;Q. Algorithms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8762950"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, one of the highlights of the conference was the opening plenary talk of Ewin Tang on dequantizing most of QML algorithms. Basically most of QML is concerned, but that just does not end the story here. The algorithms that were thought to be providing super-polynomial speed-ups don't ; but customers usually do not have asymptotic use cases ! It's just making the marketing argument a little harder, but also potentially less deceptive as asymptotics sometimes hide heavy pre-factors. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my opinion it is not a bad thing: what HPC needs is a focus on algorithms. Designing good parallel algorithms is hard in theory and in practice because you have to take care of fault, etc. Same for quantum algorithms. What dequantization tells us is that customers need to invest time and money to design algorithms that are suited to their use cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Besides E. Tang's result, several new or improved techniques for using quantum processors to simulate physics have been presented. Their interest is based on the fact that simulating even simple hamiltonian can be very hard.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have seen very impressive talks concerning NISQy devices. As such, they are good candidates to be used into actual industrial use-case studies: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Theory of Trotter Error (Andrew Childs, Yuan Su, Minh Tran, Nathan Wiebe Uma Girish, Ran Raz and Avishay Tal, Shuchen Zhu)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well -conditioned multiproduct Hamiltonian simulation  (Guang Hao Low, Vadym Kliuchnikov, Nathan Wiebe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum Imaginary Time Evolution (Mario Mota, Chong Sun, Adrian Tan, Matthew, O'Rourke , Erika Ye, Austin Minnich, Fernando Brandao and Garnet Chan)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org03671c1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org03671c1"&gt;QECC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org03671c1"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For an overview of the field head to Ben Brown's Tutorial (it contains references to major papers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several talks were devoted to the subject of tailoring codes to noise models that are encountered in today's physical systems. Ken Brow gave a very thorough overview of the matter in his plenary talk. It was later complemented by Ben Brown's third talk on high thresholds from symmetries of quantum codes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fault-tolerance was well represented. I'm probably biased as I had read the paper before, but I really enjoyed Anirudh Krishna's presentation on constructing FT gates on hypergraph product codes. The technique used generalizes code deformations and I suspect we will see it being used a lot in the months to come.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The results presented on polar codes (Frédéric Dupuis, Ashutosh Goswami, Mehdi Mhalla, Valentin Savinare) very exciting as polar codes are extremely good but (and) still require some more work to be able to be considered as first class citizens (fault tolerant gates, derandomized construction, no entanglement assistance).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbefa326" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbefa326"&gt;Other topics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbefa326"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7e9ba2c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7e9ba2c"&gt;Crypto&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7e9ba2c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personal preference for "Computationally secure and composabe remote state preparation" of Alexandru Gheorgiu and Thomas Vidick, as it is an interesting primitive for secure versions of measurement based QC. Carl Miller's work about the impossibility of weak quantum coin flipping was very impressive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orge0abcb4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge0abcb4"&gt;Estimation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge0abcb4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'd recommend "Predicting Features of Quantum Systems using Classical Shadows" (Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng) as it might reveal other ideas for quantum simulation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/highlights_from_qip/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 04:25:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Perspectives on Quantum Computing: NISQ and beyond</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/perspectives_on_quantum_computing/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgcc2fb75" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgcc2fb75"&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgcc2fb75"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM-Q classification algorithm developed for high energy physics at CERN is apparently on par with its classical counterpart (classification performance and running time).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a global shortage of talents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the proponents of superconducting qubits are happy with their solution as they think it's what's the easiest so you can focus on what goes wrong. Additionally, Google's tunable couplers really seem to help a lot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More and more discussions with industrial use-cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having one fault-tolerant logical qubit within 5 years seems a reasonable goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QC need to integrate itself into the HPC value chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6a51b55" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6a51b55"&gt;Program of the conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6a51b55"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum algorithms for the NISQ area and beyond: Iordanis Kerenidis (CNRS / QCWare)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum supremacy using a programmable superconducting processor: Charles Neill (Google Quantum AI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum computing and its applications in chemistry and physics: Ivano Tavernelli (IBM Zürich)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full-stack quantum computing with superconducting qubits: Nicolas Didier (Rigetti)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realizing fault-tolerant superconducting quantum processors: Andreas Wallraff (ETH Zürich)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programmable quantum simulators and sensors on atomic platforms: Rick van Bijnen (U. Innsbruck)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Round tables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0ab426d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0ab426d"&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0ab426d"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6acc30c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6acc30c"&gt;Iordanis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6acc30c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We currently have two kind of tools for NISQ: Euristics (QAOA and VQE) and algorithms (HHL, QML, Neural nets, …). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nothing wrong with euristics, it's just that we don't quite know how to prove the speedup. But hey, if it works in practice, it should be made available to users because they are accustomed to deal with euristics! These euristics help solving problems of optimisation under constraints (pretty much any field, from finance to transportation) for QAOA and energy minimisation problems (found in chemistry and pharma) for VQE. Both work by using a quantum machine to speedup a hybrid quantum + classical optimisation loop. Of course, for any euristics, you know it's not going to work for all problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That will imply a lot of trial and error, hence more quantum datascience in the future to bring solutions to customers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As for the algorithms based on HHL (a lot of QML), the crux is fast dataloading. In fact, these algorithms were introduced using an assumption that fast data loading was possible (ie transform classical data describing the problem to solve, to quantum usable data for the algorithm). This "fine-print" assumption came to light since Ewin Tang's dequantization paper from july 2018. It showed that the argument "Quantum computers access an exponentially large computational space hence are more powerful than their classical counterpart" fell apart: under similar "fast dataloading" assumption (in fact efficient sampling) you can find efficient classical algorithms to do the same task. But this is not the end of the story. As for euristics, if it works in practice, you should use it. And apparently, it works in practice. Iordanis reported the following figures for recommendation systems (using typical instance size): 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum: 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical: 10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantum inspired (dequantized version): 10&lt;sup&gt;33&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Main messages from Iordanis:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The key for the field now is to find something that we can run and that is impactful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications should drive the development of NISQ machines now. We cannot wait to build the machine and then start looking for use-cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org567e0fa" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org567e0fa"&gt;Charles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org567e0fa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We got a lot of pictures and explanations around the peculiarity of Google's design (superconducting). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The most interesting one (which they seem to be the only ones to have) is the presence of tunable couplers between their neighbouring qubits. This allows a "hardware" decoupling and in turn releases spots on your qubit pulse timeline to perform useful quantum operations (instead of pulsing the qubits in the background to decouple them via software). This allows for more aggressive / faster gates without decreasing the quality of them. The result is more gates per qubit. For instance: 2 qubit gates are reported at 12ns, with a 0.5 x 10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; fidelity. You can also go for more parallelism (many gates on different qubits at the same time). It also reduces the flux for applying gates and thus the cross-talk errors between qubits.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charles then talked about how Google results can be verified (since we can't use a classical computer to check the computation, and Google is the only company able to run the experiment). The approach is a physics one: Show that your error model  seems to work well up to the largest instances they can simulate classically, and that the data you get from larger instances seems to be inline. That's a good approach from a physics perspective. Not a very convincing one from the cryptographic point of view. There exists solutions for this last part though, but they are not quite focused on that yet (but they probably should).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charles went on showing chemistry applications, basically stating they are starting working on real life problems with industries. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last mentioned: their work on using a fixed always-on Hamiltonian for 22 qubits and performing analog control. Didn't quite say what the idea behind this was, but I suspect building simulators of quantum physical systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgea01388" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgea01388"&gt;Ivano&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgea01388"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part of the talk was devoted to introducing IBM's hardware and software (QisKit). One notable mention: IBM is using a superconducting architecture, but without tunable couplers. But that didn't prevent them on making progress. Their measure of performance (the quantum volume = # qubits x # gates you can apply to them) has been greatly enhanced and is on a trend of doubling every year (at least that's what the first 3 points show).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ivano's talk was impressive as they really dug into chemistry problems and trying to understand how better the quantum algorithms were. Alas, it's only for small instances as NISQ devices don't have enough computing power yet to start competing with classical software on larger molecules. But, if you take their work as a calibration phase, it is promising: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you get answers that more closely match analytical solutions (when you have them) than what the classical algorithms are able to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IBM seems to have a technique to extrapolate results from noisy computations via classical post-processing that looks interesting… or I might have misunderstood and they in fact didn't need to extrapolate and were able to get the result directly from their quantum algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again we have a lot of ad-hoc work for solving problems and see how to mitigate errors on real computations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most impressive part of the day: IBM has been partnering with CERN for classification of high energy physics events collected at ATLAS. The quantum algorithm (QSVM) is on par with the classical one in terms of quality (small advantage for the quantum one – 10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt; improvement, not quite significant). According to Ivano, there has not been much tuning done yet. On top of that it is fast (running at the micro second level). That's impressive. Looking for the details of a forthcoming paper.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6f05ddf" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6f05ddf"&gt;Nicolas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6f05ddf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Interesting presentation of their full-stack approach. It's really full-stack: designing the chip, the controllers, the PCB boards, the cryostats, … and software as well. Very similar settings and techniques to IBM and Google. They invested a lot (like the others) on error mitigation, reducing cross-talk and latency. Interestingly, they developed a parametric compiler that would compile once and reuse the result of the compiled sequence with different parameters. That would reduce greatly the latency as compiling would otherwise be needed each time you change a parameter in your gates (even though it is only a small change). They also use active reset (instead of letting their qubits decohere).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We went at length into some of their work for reducing flux noise. Long story short: they achieve a fidelity &amp;gt; .99 on their C-Z gates
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfe96fc8" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfe96fc8"&gt;Andreas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfe96fc8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One key point from Andreas is that excellent academic labs are having trouble keeping the people in academia. Part of the group was bought at once by microsoft. That's a long term problem for innovation as all the settings of Google, IBM, Rigetti are based on academic research. So there needs to be someone thinking ahead in these companies as to not deplete academia too much. On top of that, private companies have been investing way more money than academia into building devices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
About his talk: I loved it! someone interested in quantum error correction and showing how to do it. They achieved an error detection code with 7 qubits (3 ancillas, 4 logical qubits). The plan is to do error correction with 17 and 49 qubits using surface codes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The reported errors are a few percents on 2 qubit gates. For stabilizer measurements, with 2 non trivial Pauli's it's about 95%, and 81% for 4 Pauli's. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org38a4a4f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org38a4a4f"&gt;Rick&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org38a4a4f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very different approach here, but very NISQ-y. They use ion traps to simulate natural quantum processes. That means you engineer a system with some degree of control. You tune the parameters so that the effective Hamiltonian that your ions feel is related to the Hamiltonian you are interested in (if you find the solution for one, you get the solution for the second). The nice point, is that most of the problems you solve are eigenvalue / eigenvectors, hence you are in principle able to check if the solution is correct (or to which degree it is correct). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org9f5898e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9f5898e"&gt;Round tables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9f5898e"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One key point: users are not intending to buy quantum computers, but rather rent it. However, they don't want to rent it over the cloud. They want to finely understand their architecture, and limitations, as they already do for their HPC capabilities. QC makers and software companies should integrate into the HPC value chain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why superconducting: it's so simple, that you can focus on all the other things that go wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The materials bill for QC is low (a few $m). What is expensive is the knowledge you have to build to make it work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google gate performance should allow fault tolerant QC with a 1:1000 ratio. Having 1 logical qubits seems to be a reasonable goal for the next 5 yrs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to talents is hard, but education programs at ETH have proved successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/perspectives_on_quantum_computing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 03:42:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #7</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-29/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org202a922" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org202a922"&gt;General Public Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org202a922"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdf6bcc4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgdf6bcc4"&gt;A new quantum data classification protocol brings us nearer to a future 'quantum internet' – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-classification-protocol-nearer-future.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgdf6bcc4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org – Autonomous University of Barcelona&lt;/i&gt; – UAB researchers have been looking at an algorithm for data clustering for quantum states.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga681210" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga681210"&gt;Tom O'Brien explains why we need a quantum computer – &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qHJzyOU2Pls&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga681210"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Youtube – University of Leiden, Tom O'Brien&lt;/i&gt; – Good video showing why quantum computers might be efficient for quantum chemistry.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga06c63f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga06c63f"&gt;Quantum physics: Our study suggests objective reality doesn't exist – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-physics-reality-doesnt.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga06c63f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Experimental evidence that quantum reality is not a very well defined thing. In fact  the ability to reconcile two observers interpretation of their experimental results is not  granted by quantum mechanics. But it can be used as a way to detect when quantum mechanics actually become classical.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf94205c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf94205c"&gt;Nanooptical traps: A promising building block for quantum technologies – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-nanooptical-block-quantum-technologies.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf94205c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Researchers are reporting better nanooptical traps that hold atoms much longer than before. That's interesting as a way to design and control  light and matter interactions which would be used in quantum computing and quantum internet applications.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org5d5b2a6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org5d5b2a6"&gt;Quantum Volume: A Yardstick To Measure The Performance Of Quantum Computers – &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/moorinsights/2019/11/23/quantum-volume-a-yardstick-to-measure-the-power-of-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org5d5b2a6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Forbes – Paul Smith-Goodson&lt;/i&gt; – The case for quantum volume as a measure of performance for quantum hardware. That's a sensible metric pushed forward by IBMQ and Quantum Benchmark. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org975e35b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org975e35b"&gt;Researchers reach milestone in quantum standardisation – &lt;a href="https://eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2019-11/uow-rr112519.php"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org975e35b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U Waterloo&lt;/i&gt; – Well now, how do you compute the performance of quantum computers in practice (now that you know you should report quantum volume as explained in the previous entry). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org958a0c9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org958a0c9"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org958a0c9"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga7bf4cb" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga7bf4cb"&gt;IQM Finland raises €11.6 million to speed up advancements in quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://www.eu-startups.com/2019/07/iqm-finland-raises-e11-6-million-to-speed-up-advancements-in-quantum-computing/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga7bf4cb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;EU Startups – IQM Finland, Matadero QED, Maki.vc, MIG Fonds, OpenOcean, Tesi (Finnish Industry Investment), and Vito Ventures Fund&lt;/i&gt; – The startup raised money in July to build scalable cryogenic hardware for quantum computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org552227b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org552227b"&gt;For faster quantum computing, Microsoft builds a better qubit – &lt;a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/for-faster-quantum-computing-microsoft-builds-a-better-qubit/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org552227b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;CNet – Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announced to be very close to having topological qubits working. Apparently thanks to improvements in the way qubits controllers are wired.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb33c3f2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb33c3f2"&gt;HYRAX: The quantum discovery framework – &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/rahko_quantumtech-quantumsoftware-quantumcomputing-activity-6600317570186866688-NSdX/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb33c3f2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rahko&lt;/i&gt; – The recently funded company did release a framework for machine learning with backends for some of the leading quantum computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdb14694" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgdb14694"&gt;D'Arpanet à Internet : une histoire des réseaux – &lt;a href="https://interstices.info/dossier/darpanet-a-internet-une-histoire-des-reseaux/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgdb14694"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Interstices&lt;/i&gt; – In french: very interesting series of articles about ARPANET enlightning to read now that we are building a quantum internet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org5ad395c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org5ad395c"&gt;France's GDR Quantum Information from Fundamental Aspects to Experiments organised its 10th annual colloqium early november – &lt;a href="https://iqfacolloq2019.sciencesconf.org/data/pages/BoA_iqfacolloq2019_CNRS_4.pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org5ad395c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;GDR IFQA&lt;/i&gt; – Read the abstracts to have a glimpse of France's research on quantum information.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6504fde" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6504fde"&gt;NTT taps NASA to take on Google and IBM in quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://asia.nikkei.com/Business/Technology/NTT-taps-NASA-to-take-on-Google-and-IBM-in-quantum-computing"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6504fde"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nikkei Asian Review – NTT, NASA&lt;/i&gt; – NTT is partnering with NASA to develop quantum computing and go for a race with Google and IBM already quite far ahead. Interesting to see o non US based company stepping in to build a quantum computer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org798d332" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org798d332"&gt;PsiQuantum raises big money ($230m) – &lt;a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/2019/11/16/bristol-professors-secretive-quantum-computing-start-up-raises/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org798d332"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;PsiQuantum&lt;/i&gt; – PsiQuantum, founded by Jeremy O’Brien, has secured the funds from investors including a venture capital fund started by former Google executive Andy Rubin. The photonics quantum computing is increasingly looking like a feasible alternative to other technologies to built fault tolerant quantum computers. They are going to work on skipping the NISQ phase altogether.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2f4ed68" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2f4ed68"&gt;D-Wave sticks with its approach to quantum computing – &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/11/15/d-wave-sticks-with-its-approach-to-quantum-computing/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2f4ed68"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;D-Wave&lt;/i&gt; – D-Wave partnered with VW to optimise traffic at the Lisbon Websummit. Although one might discuss whether D-Wave is doing quantum computation, I think we should see the positive side of having proof of concepts that go outside labs and go to real environments. Congrats for showing the way towards computing applications for quantum devices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org02b48b6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org02b48b6"&gt;Cambridge Quantum Computing announces new release of updated software stack – &lt;a href="https://cambridgequantum.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/CQC-181119.pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org02b48b6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Cambridge Quantum Computing&lt;/i&gt; – That's a new software for designing / compiling circuits into an efficient representation suitable for being run on the major backends. This is important as these backends have topologies that make various optimisations required to get something useful. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org578a1bd" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org578a1bd"&gt;h-bar consultants published an overview of hardware QC companies funding rounds – &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hbar_consultant/status/1195889753423433728?s=09"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org578a1bd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;h-bar&lt;/i&gt; – Good to see some of them generating revenue. Doesn't mean they show a positive bottom line, just that topline is greater than 0!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga2e62af" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga2e62af"&gt;Zeiss announces a quantum challenge – &lt;a href="https://www.zeiss.com/corporate/int/careers/events/zeiss-quantum-challenge.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga2e62af"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Zeiss&lt;/i&gt; – The company is joining the quantum fun with a challenge centered on sensing and imaging. Deadline is march 31st 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org683ef7f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org683ef7f"&gt;Xanadu receives grant from DARPA to test QML on quantum hardware – &lt;a href="https://betakit.com/xanadu-receives-grant-from-darpa-to-test-qml-performance-on-quantum-hardware/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org683ef7f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu, DARPA&lt;/i&gt; – The research project is expected to last 12 months.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgac2dd07" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgac2dd07"&gt;Research Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgac2dd07"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0f9a9de" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0f9a9de"&gt;Characterizing large-scale quantum computers via cycle benchmarking – &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-13068-7"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0f9a9de"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Alexander Erhard, Joel J. Wallman, Lukas Postler, Michael Meth, Roman Stricker, Esteban A. Martinez, Philipp Schindler, Thomas Monz, Joseph Emerson &amp;amp; Rainer Blatt&lt;/i&gt; – How do you benchmark the quality of quantum gates involving more that 3 - 4 qubits ? If you do tomography with imperfect state preparation and measurements, it will take for ever. Cycle benchmarking is an interesting option and has been demonstrated experimentally on ion trap QC. Related to the last entry of the General Public Articles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org216b96c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org216b96c"&gt;Positions - Conferences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org216b96c"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6429d64" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6429d64"&gt;Quantum Computing Theory in Practice Conference – &lt;a href="https://riverlane.io/qctip-conference/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6429d64"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Centre for Mathematical Sciences, Cambridge | 6-8 April 2020
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgeb86181" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgeb86181"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgeb86181"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf8e347a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf8e347a"&gt;Neutrinos Lead to Unexpected Discovery in Basic Math – &lt;a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/neutrinos-lead-to-unexpected-discovery-in-basic-math-20191113/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf8e347a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quanta Magazine – Stephen Parke (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory), Xining Zhang (University of Chicago), Peter Denton (Brookhaven National Laboratory)&lt;/i&gt; – A beautiful fundamental result in linear algebra, giving a simple way of expressing the eigenvectors of a matrix in terms of the eigenvalues of that matrix and some submatrices.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2e03cce" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2e03cce"&gt;Quantum light improves sensitivity of biological measurements – &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-11-quantum-sensitivity-biological.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2e03cce"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Research on single photon source finds use in biology to track enzymatic reaction in real-tine. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-29/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #6</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-19/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orge020ed5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge020ed5"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge020ed5"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1695c28" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1695c28"&gt;The hard sell of quantum software – &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/the-hard-sell-of-quantum-software/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1695c28"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Phys.org&lt;/i&gt; – Why are people founding so many start-ups to build quantum software ? What are the potential use cases and what are the short term focus for these companies ?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6c257f3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6c257f3"&gt;Here’s what the people who claimed Google’s quantum supremacy have to say about it – &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2019/10/inside-googles-quantum-computing-efforts/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6c257f3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Google Quantum AI Lab - Ars Technica&lt;/i&gt; – Nice article with lots of pictures from inside Google's lab. Fair account on the challenges faced for hardware and software componenets, and surprisingly (or not), wiring comes out as one of the most challenging ones. But that doesn't look like it's unsolvable though when you add industrial engineering and processing. You can also read Google's blog post about their experieent and settings &lt;a href="https://ai.googleblog.com/2019/10/quantum-supremacy-using-programmable.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org63d91fa" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org63d91fa"&gt;Quantum internet: at the verge of an emerging technology – &lt;a href="https://blog.qutech.nl/index.php/2019/10/22/quantum-internet-at-the-verge-of-an-emerging-technology/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org63d91fa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;QuTech, TU Delft&lt;/i&gt; – Nice article showing what use cases of a quantum internet will be: QKD and all sorts of cryptographic protocols, but most importantly Delegated Quantum Computation. Sensing and metrology are also on the list. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org384fb13" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org384fb13"&gt;Google and IBM are at odds over ‘quantum supremacy’ – an expert explains what it really means – &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/google-and-ibm-are-at-odds-over-quantum-supremacy-an-expert-explains-what-it-really-means-125827"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org384fb13"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;T. Cubitt - The Conversation&lt;/i&gt; – JUst a quote from the short article: "This is how science and technology progresses. Not in one dramatic and revolutionary breakthrough, but in a whole series of small breakthroughs, with the academic community carefully scrutinising, criticising and refining each step along the way. Only a few of these advances and debates hit the headlines. The reality is both less dramatic and more interesting."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfcae927" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgfcae927"&gt;Quantum Computer Made from Photons Achieves a New Record – &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/quantum-computer-made-from-photons-achieves-a-new-record/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgfcae927"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. Science and Technology, China – Scientific American&lt;/i&gt; – The development of photonic quantum computing is impressive. There you trade low temperatures for extreme timing accuracy. The pro is that photons in the vaccuum are essentially decoherence free. The con is that you need to find a clever way to have photon-photon gates… 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orga4b6255" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga4b6255"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga4b6255"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org13a4655" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org13a4655"&gt;Alphabet's X is contributing to port some quantum tools to tensorflow – &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/TensorNetwork"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org13a4655"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;X&lt;/i&gt; – Jack Hidary mentionned that the work of G. Vidal on tensor networks is being turned into a module accessible through tensor flow to help making large simulations of quantum systems easier to perform on classical computers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbf73940" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbf73940"&gt;Quantum Benchmark supports development of Google’s world-leading quantum computers – &lt;a href="https://quantumbenchmark.com/quantum-benchmark-supports-development-of-googles-world-leading-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbf73940"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Quantum Benchmark, Google Quantum AI Lab&lt;/i&gt; – QUantum Benchmark is working with Google to improve gate efficiency and compiling. Great partnership.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org5fdec24" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org5fdec24"&gt;HPE announces investment into IonQ – &lt;a href="https://www.hpe.com/us/en/newsroom/blog-post/2019/10/shaping-the-quantum-future.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org5fdec24"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ &amp;amp; HPE&lt;/i&gt; – HPE is making the choice of Trapped Ion technology as a better way to scale quantum computing experiements to commercially useful machines. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org97af8d1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org97af8d1"&gt;Volkswagen optimizes traffic flow with quantum computers – &lt;a href="https://www.volkswagen-newsroom.com/en/press-releases/volkswagen-optimizes-traffic-flow-with-quantum-computers-5507"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org97af8d1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;VW &amp;amp; D-Wave&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum computing in practice wit VW optimizing traffic in Lisbon during the WebSummit conference. It still remains to be seen how better it solves the problem compared to classical optimization.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4195c32" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4195c32"&gt;Xanadu is expanding it's pennylane software to include Cirq support – &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/xanaduai_xanaduaipennylane-cirq-activity-6595352592212127744-ejwx/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4195c32"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu&lt;/i&gt; – Pennylane is now able to interact with Cirq (google's framework) so you can actually optimize a full quantum-classical hybrid algo using Cirq / Forest / Qiskit and the usual Tensorflow and Pytorch tools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2a353ab" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2a353ab"&gt;Experience quantum impact with Azure Quantum – &lt;a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/quantum/2019/11/04/announcing-microsoft-azure-quantum/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2a353ab"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announces the launch of Azure Quantum. Yet another player going for a cloud offering for quantum computing. This is a major change compared to when classical computing started. Quantum computing is being built on top of a very rich stack of computing and communication experience. In my opinion, this makes quantum communication and quantum computation inseparable topics, both requiring attention and investments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orge83a78a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orge83a78a"&gt;IonQ Partners with Microsoft to Power Azure Quantum – &lt;a href="https://ionq.com/news/november-4-2019-microsoft-partnership"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orge83a78a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ &amp;amp; Microsoft&lt;/i&gt; – A partnership to make Azure Quantum, well… quantum ! Two big hits for IonQ (HPE and Microsoft). Is that the revenge of the trapped Ions ? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef09eeb" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgef09eeb"&gt;Micorsoft partners with Honeywell – &lt;a href="https://www.honeywell.com/en-us/newsroom/news/2019/11/the-future-of-quantum-computing?utm_source=TW&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=newsroom&amp;amp;utm_term=msquantum&amp;amp;sf111836522=1"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgef09eeb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Microsoft &amp;amp; Honeywell&lt;/i&gt; – Microsoft announces its partnership with Honeywell "to bring about quantum impact through Azure Quantum" (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/krystasvore/status/1191425045970612224?s=09"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org25e994a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org25e994a"&gt;AQT now supports Qiskit – &lt;a href="https://www.aqt.eu/aqt-now-supports-qiskit/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org25e994a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;AQT&lt;/i&gt; – Alpine Quantum Computing develops an Ion trap quantum computer. It reports of its compatibility with IBM qiskit devevelopment tools suite.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb06396f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb06396f"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb06396f"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4a2856d" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4a2856d"&gt;List of accepted papers at QIP2020 – &lt;a href="http://www.szpclab.com/qip2020#/programDetails"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4a2856d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Impressive and exciting list. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org38cab21" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org38cab21"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org38cab21"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org39379ea" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org39379ea"&gt;PostDoc position at the Center for Theoretical Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences – &lt;a href="http://www.cft.edu.pl/new/public/links/aHR0cHMlM0ElMkYlMkZjZnRwYW4uYmlwLmdvdi5wbCUyRmZvYmplY3RzJTJGZG93bmxvYWQlMkY2NTk0NjElMkZhbm5vdW5jZW1lbnQtYWJvdXQtdGhlLWNvbXBldGl0aW9uLmh0bWw=/display"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org39379ea"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;CTP, Polish Academy of Sciences&lt;/i&gt; – 
Announcement from Remigiusz Augusiak, to work on quantum information theory, quantum entanglement, Bell nonlocality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-11-19/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 05:29:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Qoherences #5</title><link>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-24/</link><dc:creator>Harold Ollivier</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org91ef3c2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org91ef3c2"&gt;Hot / Not Hot / Hot Again News&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org91ef3c2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
IBM claims in &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.09534"&gt;arXiv/1910/09534&lt;/a&gt; that Google's quantum supremacy computation is not so supreme. They optimized the classical simulation and went down to 2.5 days instead of 10000+ years. So: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are much better at optmizing classical simulations of quantum algorithms than google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They did not make remarks on the quantum part, nor did they decrease the amount of elementary operations necessary to simulate the quantum computation (complexity is unchanged)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3.5 minutes is 1000 times less than 2.5 days (Google's computation is performed 1000 times faster than what the supercomputer SUMMIT is able to achieve).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you conclude whether the quantum supremacy claim from Google still holds. &lt;a href="https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/breaking-the-breaking-news-or-not/"&gt;More details&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, Google has published its supremacy result – &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-019-1666-5?fbclid=IwAR30gYaaQUI-uIAnd7e9UajLkGPXKnTKF3bqVKjajTOA1YcJK17UUYIUHxs"&gt;Nature 574, pages 505–510 (2019)&lt;/a&gt; –, and politely answered to IBM's paper saying they welcome comments on how to optimize classical algorithms, but it's better to actually test them to be sure of what you are gaining. Apparently Google's estimate was done using real sample data from supercomputers which IBM didn't do in their paper. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf3d2c4c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf3d2c4c"&gt;General public articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf3d2c4c"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org2e10b80" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2e10b80"&gt;Beyond quantum supremacy: the hunt for useful quantum computers - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02936-3"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2e10b80"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature - Michael Brooks&lt;/i&gt; – While some are debating about quantum supremacy, others are trying to find out how to put small imperfect devices to work for solving real-world problem. A good overview of the quantum algorithm landscape.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd7214d7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd7214d7"&gt;Next-generation single-photon source for quantum information science - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-next-generation-single-photon-source-quantum-science.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd7214d7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science Advances - P. Kwiat (U. of Illinois), F. Kaneda (Tohoku U.)&lt;/i&gt; – Reliable single photon sources are extremely important for quantum communication, but hard to make. Using time multiplexing Kwiat's team managed to increase the efficiency of the process to the point where they could get several thousands of 12-photon events per second.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf351a3f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf351a3f"&gt;Quantum Threat Timeline - &lt;a href="https://globalriskinstitute.org/publications/quantum-threat-timeline/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf351a3f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;M Mosca and M Piani (EvolutionQ)&lt;/i&gt; – Research report published by the Global Risk Institute, trying to assess the quantum threat over classic cryptosystems. About 50% of the experts think that quantum computers will be threat for the current cryptosystems within 15 years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf946ee1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf946ee1"&gt;Tracking Entanglement in a Quantum Simulator - &lt;a href="https://www.osa-opn.org/home/newsroom/2018/april/tracking_entanglement_in_a_quantum_simulator/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf946ee1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Optics &amp;amp; Photonics - IQOQI (Innsbruck)&lt;/i&gt; – Report on a 20-qubit trapped ions experiment and the difficulty to know if a quantum device is behaving properly. Using a brute force approach would be equivalent to simulate the evolution of the quantum systems classically: fairly inefficient. By using the right (cryptographic) setting and tools, you can manage to do this much more efficiently.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7d3d32f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7d3d32f"&gt;New Encryption System Protects Data from Quantum Computers - &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/new-encryption-system-protects-data-from-quantum-computers/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7d3d32f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IBM Research Zurich - Vadim Lyubashevsky&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum algorithms are moving the world! The impact of algorithms not yet implemented shook the crypto community when the NIST asked in 2016 for new quantum-safe crytosystems to be proposed for a public release in 2024. IBM is reporting on their proposal called CRYSTALS that should be implemented in its cloud solutions by 2020.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org4e5b3b6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org4e5b3b6"&gt;Cryptography without using secret keys - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-cryptography-secret-keys.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org4e5b3b6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U. of Twente - W.r. Van Der Veen&lt;/i&gt; – Cryptography can make use of physically uncloneable functions for authentication and encryption. Here is a brief account about what this is and how it is done. Although there is a lot of quantum in there, the function (key in the article) is still classical. Quantum people have devised quantum attacks on such devices and also &lt;a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2019/1181"&gt;quantum PUF&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0ebc0bc" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0ebc0bc"&gt;Weaving quantum processors out of laser light - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-quantum-processors-laser.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0ebc0bc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science DOI: 10.1126/science.aay2645 - Centre for Quantum Computation &amp;amp; Communication Technology, Nicolas Menicucci - U Tokyo - U New Mexico&lt;/i&gt; – The University of Melbourne CQC2T is reporting the creation of a large photonic cluster state. Cluster states are resources that can be used for implementing measurement based quantum computations. The nice thing is all the complicated stuff is made at the begining through the creation of this horribly entangled state. Using it is then much simpler as it requires only single qubit measurements and classically single qubit gates. This is quite an achievement and very motivating to see that fundamentally different architectures are subject of research.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3eddf5c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3eddf5c"&gt;Blanket of light may give better quantum computers - &lt;a href="https://phys.org/news/2019-10-blanket-quantum.html"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3eddf5c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Science DOI: 10.1126/science.aay4354 - BigQ (Denmark), Ulrik Lund Andersen&lt;/i&gt;  – The Danes have done the same as the Aussies. Or is it the other way around. Impressive anyways: we are talking of 30 000 entangled light pulses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org26a63e0" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org26a63e0"&gt;Industry - Academia - Startups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org26a63e0"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc24572a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc24572a"&gt;Barclays demonstrates proof-of-concept quantum clearing algorithm - &lt;a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/news/252472462/Barclays-demonstrates-proof-of-concept-quantum-clearing-algorithm"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc24572a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Barclays, IBM&lt;/i&gt; – Looks like they have found a use for small scale quantum computer. Need to read the original &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.05788v1.pdf"&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org482f4ca" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org482f4ca"&gt;Toshiba France advertises its QKD solution -  &lt;a href="https://www.toshiba.fr/?utm_source=cpc&amp;amp;utm_medium=linkedin&amp;amp;utm_campaign=fy19b&amp;amp;utm_content=qkd"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org482f4ca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Toshiba&lt;/i&gt; – Interesting to see industries picking up the subject. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org46509e4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org46509e4"&gt;Rahko raises £1.3M seed from Balderton for quantum machine learning tech - &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/10/11/rahko-raises-1-3m-seed-from-balderton-for-quantum-machine-learning-tech/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org46509e4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rahko, Balderton Capital&lt;/i&gt; – Interesting to see a Series A VC fund invest in a seed round. VC's are probably seeing the quantum ecosystem as sufficiently small and the prospects with large corporations sufficiently interesting to make such unusual move. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3bf8561" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3bf8561"&gt;IonQ Secures $55 Million in Funding to Bring Quantum Computing from the Lab to the Enterprise - &lt;a href="https://ionq.com/news/october-22-2019-new-funding"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3bf8561"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IonQ -  Samsung Catalyst Fund and Mubadala Capital&lt;/i&gt; – $55m raised in this round, $77m total. That's serious money now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org51b3e0f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org51b3e0f"&gt;Quantum photonics hardware developer Nu Quantum raises pre-seed investment - &lt;a href="https://www.amadeuscapital.com/quantum-photonics-hardware-developer-nu-quantum-raises-pre-seed-investment/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org51b3e0f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nu Quantum, Amadeus Capital Partners, with participation from IQ Capital, Ahren Capital, Cambridge Enterprise and Martlet Capital&lt;/i&gt; – 650k pounds raised in a seed round for building single photon sources and detectors, which are the building blocks of quantum networks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1693562" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1693562"&gt;Strathclyde quantum technology partnership secures £4.6 million - &lt;a href="https://www.strath.ac.uk/whystrathclyde/news/strathclydequantumtechnologypartnershipsecures46million/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1693562"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;U Strathclyde - Msquared&lt;/i&gt; – A U Strathclyde + Msquared partnership secured funding worth a total of £4.6 million.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbedec72" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbedec72"&gt;HQS Quantum Simulations Closes €2.3 Million Seed Financing Round - &lt;a href="https://quantumsimulations.de/news/2019/10/hqs-closes-seed-financing-round/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbedec72"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;HQS Quantum Simulations&lt;/i&gt; – Designing software for quantum computer assisted material designs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orga27ea63" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orga27ea63"&gt;Xanadu releases a new quantum machine learning library for python - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pennylaneai/status/1186371620157493251?s=09"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orga27ea63"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Xanadu&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdca4792" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdca4792"&gt;Research papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdca4792"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7182a54" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7182a54"&gt;Variational Fast Forwarding for Quantum Simulation Beyond the Coherence Time - &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.04292"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7182a54"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;LANL - Cristina Cirstoiu, Zoe Holmes, Joseph Iosue, Lukasz Cincio, Patrick J. Coles, Andrew Sornborger&lt;/i&gt; – A new technique for simulating the evolution of quantum physical systems with noisy intermediate scale quantum computers that allows to go beyond the decoherence time of the quantum machines. Very cool!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org6735425" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6735425"&gt;Learning the quantum algorithm for state overlap - &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1367-2630/aae94a/pdf"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6735425"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;LANL - Lukasz Cincio, Yiğit Subaş, Andrew T Sornborger and Patrick J Coles&lt;/i&gt; – Same group of people from Los Alamos. This one would help finding new circuits and serve as a guide for compiling high-level functions into device specific sequences of commands. Very promising (has led already to many follow-ups by the same group. Wondering how it can be adapted to make it work for optimizing communication protocols.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb751b76" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb751b76"&gt;Circuit-Based Quantum Random Access Memory for Classical Data - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-019-40439-3"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb751b76"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;ITRC of Quantum Computing for AI, KAIST Korea - Daniel K. Park, Francesco Petruccione &amp;amp; June-Koo Kevin Rhee&lt;/i&gt; – Using quantum algorithms for solving real-world problems requires making classical data available to it. This paper describes a possible architecture for loading classical data into a quantum memory in an efficient way. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb140c9c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb140c9c"&gt;Positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb140c9c"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org1966809" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1966809"&gt;PostDoc Positions at IQC (U. Waterloo) - &lt;a href="https://services.iqc.uwaterloo.ca/applications/positions/iqc-postdoctoral-fellowship/"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1966809"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IQC&lt;/i&gt; – Theory.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org3470f24" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3470f24"&gt;PostDoc Positions at IRIF (U. Paris) - &lt;a href="https://www.irif.fr/en/postes/postdoc"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3470f24"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;IRIF&lt;/i&gt; – Quantum machine learning, optimization, quantum communications and cryptography.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org781598b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org781598b"&gt;JQE Software internship at Rigetti - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rigetti/status/1186672593039847424?s=09"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org781598b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rigetti&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9a6f0bc" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9a6f0bc"&gt;Miscellanea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9a6f0bc"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc6ed2fe" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc6ed2fe"&gt;Quantum USA Vs. Quantum China: The World's Most Important Technology Race - &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/moorinsights/2019/10/10/quantum-usa-vs-quantum-china-the-worlds-most-important-technology-race/#135e818f72de"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc6ed2fe"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Forbes&lt;/i&gt; –  US views on the investments by China into quantum technology.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org9ef629a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9ef629a"&gt;L'écosystème français de l'informatique quantique : ses atouts, ses faiblesses &lt;a href="https://www.latribune.fr/technos-medias/innovation-et-start-up/l-ecosysteme-francais-de-l-informatique-quantique-ses-atouts-ses-faiblesses-831271.html?utm_term=Autofeed&amp;amp;utm_medium=Social&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter#Echobox=1571760787"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9ef629a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;La Tribune&lt;/i&gt; – more or less accurate description of the french ecosystem. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org85139b6" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org85139b6"&gt;Quantum gold rush: the private funding pouring into quantum start-ups - &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02935-4?utm_source=twt_nnc&amp;amp;utm_medium=social&amp;amp;utm_campaign=naturenews&amp;amp;sf220597140=1"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org85139b6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Nature doi: 10.1038/d41586-019-02935-4&lt;/i&gt; – 2017 and 2018 have seen 52 companies funded for $450m fresh money. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbbd0426" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbbd0426"&gt;The hard sell of quantum software - &lt;a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/the-hard-sell-of-quantum-software/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbbd0426"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;PhysicsWorld&lt;/i&gt; – Tries to explain why VCs invest in quantum software companies. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://h-oll.github.io/qoherences/posts/2019-10-24/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>